<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The good vvife: or, A rare one amongst women VVhereto is annexed an exquisite discourse of epitaphs: including the choisest thereof, ancient or moderne. Musophilus.</title>
            <author>Brathwaite, Richard, 1588?-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11746</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840373</idno>
  <idno type="VID">178199</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240900539</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 3568.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S104640</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99840373e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11746)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178199)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1477:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The good vvife: or, A rare one amongst women VVhereto is annexed an exquisite discourse of epitaphs: including the choisest thereof, ancient or moderne. Musophilus.</title>
                  <author>Brathwaite, Richard, 1588?-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Beale] for Richard Redmer, and are to be sold at his shop at the west end of St Pauls Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-K L⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>The title page verso has a table of contents. Variant 1: title page verso is blank.</note>
                  <note>"Remains after death" has separate dated title page with "Imprinted .. by Iohn Beale" in the imprint; register is continuous. The latter title page has "By Richard Brathvvayte Gent.". Variant 2: author's name given as "Musophilus".</note>
                  <note>"Remains after death" identified as STC 3582 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>"Remains after death" only.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Wives --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Epitaphs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178199:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178199:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:178199:2"/>
            <p>THE Good Wife: OR, <hi>A rare one amongst Women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereto is annexed an <hi>Exquisite Discourse of</hi> EPITAPHS: Including the choisest thereof, Ancient or Moderne.</p>
            <q>Vxor bona chara supellex.</q>
            <p>MVSOPHILVS.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for RICHARD REDMER, and are to be sold at his shop at the West end of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Church. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:178199:3"/>
            <head>¶ The distinct Sections in <hi>this Booke contained.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The good Wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Obseruations vpon Epitaphs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Epitaphs.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The Prodigals Glasse.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Mourners Meane.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:178199:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>VNderstand (Gentle Reader) that this <hi>Treatise</hi> was long since intended for the Presse, but vpon the publishing of that iudicious and sententious <hi>Poem</hi> writ by the worthy decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed knight Sir <hi>Thomas Ouerberie</hi> neerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with <hi>this</hi> in <hi>Title,</hi> though in matter and manner different: It was thought meete to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained till better opportunitie (which is now afforded) might giue it liberty to be reuiued. Receiue <hi>it</hi> then as it was first intended, and so may the Authors labor to <hi>thee</hi> directed, be by thy prayers mutually requited.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:4"/>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In pursuit of Loues enquest,</l>
                     <l>Heauy-eyde <hi>Musophilus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Restlesse takes himselfe to rest,</l>
                     <l>And desplaies his fortunes thus.</l>
                     <l>Jn his sleepe (deaths shade) appeares</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Age,</hi> the honour of mans life,</l>
                     <l>Old in houres as well as yeares,</l>
                     <l>Who instructs him in a <hi>Wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in briefe assaies to show,</l>
                     <l>Who is <hi>good,</hi> who is not so.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Next his choice, he shewes his Sonne,</l>
                     <l>(Lest he should his choice neglect)</l>
                     <l>What by him ought to be done</l>
                     <l>To his <hi>Wife</hi> in each respect,</l>
                     <l>Who though <hi>shee</hi> should euer feare</l>
                     <l>To giue cause of iust offence,</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>he</hi> ought not domineere</l>
                     <l>'Cause he has preheminence;</l>
                     <l>For that conquest's worthy no man,</l>
                     <l>Where they triumph o're a woman.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Age retires, yet in retire,</l>
                     <l>Wakes close-eyde Musophilus,</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>he</hi> sees whom his desire</l>
                     <l>Bids <hi>him</hi> wooe and wooing chuse:</l>
                     <l>Woo'd and won, he doth inuite</l>
                     <l>Such as aime at vertuous ends,</l>
                     <l>To be present at the Rite</l>
                     <l>Of two selfe-vnited friends.</l>
                     <l>Who if they will, come they may,</l>
                     <l>If they will not, they may stay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poems">
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:4"/>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>
                        <hi>A good VVife, Or</hi> A rare one amongst Women.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>DOwne by a vale a pleasant shade there was,</l>
                        <l>By which a silent siluer streamling past,</l>
                        <l>Where I retir'd and sate me on the grasse,</l>
                        <l>Whilest my deiected eye with sleepe lockt fast,</l>
                        <l>Presented thousand obiects where I was;</l>
                        <l>'Mongst which a grauer <hi>Module</hi> then the rest</l>
                        <l>Appear'd to me, and made it thus exprest.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A graue olde man of reuerend aspect,</l>
                        <l>Whose yeeres imported somthing that was good,</l>
                        <l>In sable habit, shewing his neglect</l>
                        <l>"Of earthly Fortunes, as an obiect stood,</l>
                        <l>To caution me (me thought) of that respect</l>
                        <l>Which I should haue, and euer ought to haue</l>
                        <l>Of my times <hi>Mansion, Frailty,</hi> and my <hi>Graue.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Sithe, an houre-glasse and a waterpot,</l>
                        <l>A fatall <hi>Deaths-head, Shrowding-sheete</hi> and <hi>Bere,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>An vrne of mouldred ashes, which were got</l>
                        <l>From some darke charnell house as 't did appeare,</l>
                        <l>Where on was writ, <hi>This is our frailties lot,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This's all we shall possesse of all our store,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This beggers haue, and Princes haue no more.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:5"/>
                        <l>These were the <hi>reliks</hi> which this old mā brought</l>
                        <l>Which oft he mou'd and brandish'd ouer me,</l>
                        <l>And still by teares he seem'd as if he sought</l>
                        <l>To caution me of my mortalitie,</l>
                        <l>But 'las his teares still drown'd his speech me thought,</l>
                        <l>Till he at last by <hi>force</hi> did silence breake,</l>
                        <l>And to me sleeping thus began to speake:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Good rest my Sonne, yet (Sonne) retire from rest,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And heare thy Father, pray thee then awake,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For though I me deade, yet is my loue exprest</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Euen in my death; then for thy Fathers sake,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lay vp these last instructions in thy brest,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which with obseruance if thou keepe, they may</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cheere thee both heere, and in the latter day.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou knowest my Sonne, though thou wert <hi>last in birth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou wert not <hi>least</hi> in my affection too,</l>
                        <l>Witnesse my <hi>care</hi> of thee, while I on earth,</l>
                        <l>Soiorned there in that same vale of woe;</l>
                        <l>Yea, I may say, euen in my comforts dearth,</l>
                        <l>When grieues and sorrowes did enuiron me,</l>
                        <l>Which frustrate hopes supplied their hope in <hi>thee.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor could I thinke so many a widdows praier,</l>
                        <l>Orphanes well wishes, and the poore-mans vow,</l>
                        <l>Would turne my fruit of hope into despaire,</l>
                        <l>Since vowes, praiers, wishes, did distinctly show</l>
                        <l>Their <hi>loue</hi> to me for my deuoutest care,</l>
                        <l>Which from my heart I euer aimed at,</l>
                        <l>To right their wrongs, and setle their estate.</l>
                        <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:5"/>
                        <l>O let my hopes then now in my decease,</l>
                        <l>Confirme my Blessing which I gaue to thee;</l>
                        <l>So shall thy Soule enioy that soueraigne peace</l>
                        <l>Which was prepar'd 'fore all eternitie,</l>
                        <l>For such as made a prosperous encrease</l>
                        <l>In euery vertuous action, which Ile show</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Succinctly to thee in a word or two.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>First then <hi>my Sonne,</hi> because I finde thee here</l>
                        <l>In th'Ile <hi>Foolonia,</hi> where so many come,</l>
                        <l>VVhose names &amp; Natures with the Ile cohere,</l>
                        <l>I must by way aduertise thee of <hi>some</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>VVho (in disguise) not as themselues appeare</l>
                        <l>Earths polititians, who'l not stand to staine</l>
                        <l>Their soules pure lustre for a little gaine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>These can dispēce with faith, &amp; wil profes</l>
                        <l>What they least thinke: to guild their guile they'l swear:</l>
                        <l>Yet be their oathes shrowdes to licentiousnesse,</l>
                        <l>(Which thogh they seem a faire pretēce to beare,)</l>
                        <l>Take but their vizard off, they're nothing lesse,</l>
                        <l>Then what they did protest: Beware of them,</l>
                        <l>For these be dangerous <hi>Hollow harted men.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet these be fooles, though they be politike,</l>
                        <l>In that they aime more at a priuate good,</l>
                        <l>A sensuall pleasure, honour, or such like,</l>
                        <l>Then at that <hi>supreame end,</hi> which vnderstood,</l>
                        <l>VVould their conceits to admiration strike;</l>
                        <l>For weak's their iudgement, and ele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tion rash,</l>
                        <l>That poize souls treasure lesse thē worlds trash.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:6"/>
                        <l>Next vnto these, be <hi>such</hi> as doe aspire</l>
                        <l>Aboue their pitch, and with ambitious wings</l>
                        <l>So are far aboue their sphere: <hi>these</hi> do desire</l>
                        <l>Nought more then to be popular, which brings</l>
                        <l>A timelesse merited end, for they conspire</l>
                        <l>Their owne subuersion: <hi>for few euer haue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ambition sene graye-headed to her graue.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>These reach at Scepters</hi> but <hi>do ofttimes fall</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Below their Center,</hi> and though they do make</l>
                        <l>Their owne opinions Axioms, and will call</l>
                        <l>Nought good, but what themselues do vndertake</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet by a publiqe verdit, when they shall</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Conuicted bee,</hi> then they'le confesse &amp; say,</l>
                        <l>Non (thogh more seemin-gwise,) more fools thē they.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Next these be <hi>Prodigals,</hi> who spend their time</l>
                        <l>Like <hi>Circes chanted guests:</hi> these are but men</l>
                        <l>Onely in <hi>forme,</hi> for th' part which is diuine,</l>
                        <l>Remaines obscure and darker shines in them</l>
                        <l>Then a small <hi>star cloath'd in a cloud doth shine.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>These men we well may <hi>formal shadowes call,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For saue meere <hi>shadowes,</hi> these are nought at all.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Aleynous</hi> mates, such as were borne to bee</l>
                        <l>But not to liue, pageants that goe and moue,</l>
                        <l>And weare good cloath's, yet view thē inwardly,</l>
                        <l>They are but Trunks at best, or Apes, that loue</l>
                        <l>Or make a shew of loue, whose ends we see,</l>
                        <l>When they haue run on shelfe their whole estate</l>
                        <l>Their <hi>Brothell greeting</hi>'s changd into a <hi>grate.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:6"/>
                        <l>And are not <hi>these</hi> vaine <hi>fooles,</hi> that make a losse</l>
                        <l>Of credit, bodie, state, to yeeld delight</l>
                        <l>For one poor moment? ô when they shall tosse</l>
                        <l>Those leaue of their account where appetite</l>
                        <l>Made them insensate and that weeping crosse,</l>
                        <l>Which their profuser follies brought them to,</l>
                        <l>They'le style themselues then <hi>Fooles in folio.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Next be <hi>these staines of honour,</hi> which defile</l>
                        <l>Those Temples which ought to be dedicate</l>
                        <l>To an Ethereall power: <hi>These though they'ue stile</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of women are nought lesse, for why they hate</l>
                        <l>What best beseemes that sex: &amp; hence this Ile</l>
                        <l>Deriues her Name (and aptly doth it take,)</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When th'stronger sexe is ruled by the weake.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>These</hi> are <hi>those lures</hi> of death which drawe men on</l>
                        <l>Vnto perdition; <hi>These</hi> are they that show</l>
                        <l>Like Flowers in <hi>May,</hi> but they are withered soon</l>
                        <l>(Euen with one breth, for painting (if you blow)</l>
                        <l>Makes the Complexion to be quite vndone:</l>
                        <l>Vnhappie <hi>she</hi> that when <hi>she</hi> sees one breath</l>
                        <l>Dissolues her varnish, will not think on death.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Of these <hi>my sonne</hi> no more will I relate</l>
                        <l>Then what I haue: now meane I to descend</l>
                        <l>To teach thee somthing for thy own estate</l>
                        <l>And how thou maist be to thy selfe a friend</l>
                        <l>With a good Conscience, which to violate</l>
                        <l>Were worst of euills: and to forme thy life</l>
                        <l>Better, <hi>I'le tell thee how to chuse a wife.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:7"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> thou thy wife <hi>(my Sonne)</hi> nor <hi>faire</hi> nor <hi>foule,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor gay nor sluttish; silent, yet knowes when</l>
                        <l>And where it's fit to speak, one whose chaste soule</l>
                        <l>Shews modestie in blushes, and will len</l>
                        <l>No eare to light affections, but can coole</l>
                        <l>Heate of desire (for such desires may bee</l>
                        <l>In purest loue) by her enioying thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> a fixt eye, for wandring lookes display</l>
                        <l>A wauering disposition; let her cheeke</l>
                        <l>Be without art: <hi>Chuse</hi> me a bashfull <hi>nay</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Before a quick assent; for such as seeke</l>
                        <l>Husbands, for feare they should too long time stay,</l>
                        <l>Resemble <hi>those</hi> who know their ware is worst,</l>
                        <l>And therefore mean to sell't to whō comes first.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one that's so discreet knows when to spare,</l>
                        <l>VVhen to expresse herselfe in bountie, so</l>
                        <l>As neither niggard-nature may haue share</l>
                        <l>In her, nor lauishnes, when shees'd bestow</l>
                        <l>What <hi>Reputation</hi> claimes, which speciall care</l>
                        <l>Imports a soueraigne complement or end</l>
                        <l>To <hi>such,</hi> know when &amp; where to spare or spend.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> thee no gadder (for a wife should bee</l>
                        <l>In this respect (I'me sure) like to a Snaile,)</l>
                        <l>VVho (hous-wifelike) still in her house we see;</l>
                        <l>For if her care or prouidence do faile,</l>
                        <l>Her howse-affaires will go disorderlie,</l>
                        <l>And hardlie can <hi>that VVife</hi> endure to stay</l>
                        <l>In her owne house, whose minde's another way.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:7"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> thee no liquorish Gossip, whose delight</l>
                        <l>Is how to please her taste, for seldome can</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>One</hi> that's exposed to her appetite</l>
                        <l>Conforme her to the state of any man,</l>
                        <l>VVhich to an honest minde would be a spite,</l>
                        <l>That when thou wish's thy wife a competent</l>
                        <l>Fitting her ranke, she will not be content.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> thee no coy precisian, she is too smooth</l>
                        <l>To proue sincere, in simpringst looks we finde</l>
                        <l>Oft most deceit, for these (as th'water doth</l>
                        <l>Seeme calmest where thei're deepest) let thy minde</l>
                        <l>Be so prepar'd, as thou wilt euer loath</l>
                        <l>Such formalists, <hi>She-doctors,</hi> who haue sought</l>
                        <l>To teach far more then euer they were taught.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> thee no wanton that will prostitute</l>
                        <l>Her soule for sensuall pleasure, there attends</l>
                        <l>Nought vpon <hi>such,</hi> but blasting of repute,</l>
                        <l>Horrid diseases, miserable ends,</l>
                        <l>With which their vicious liues doe euer sute,</l>
                        <l>And worst of worsts, that <hi>issue</hi> which is got</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Such,</hi> may seeme thine owne, but it is not.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> thee no <hi>VVife</hi> that is selfe-singular</l>
                        <l>She'le be her owne instructresse, and in that</l>
                        <l>Shee (through presumption) will be bold to erre,</l>
                        <l>Hating reproofe, which will orethrow thy state,</l>
                        <l>Beware <hi>(my Sonne)</hi> thou shalt be tide to her,</l>
                        <l>Which seruitude (though it be too to common)</l>
                        <l>Disualues man that's subiect to a woman.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:8"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one for vertue (though a Portion's good)</l>
                        <l>Yet deare's the Portion if thy <hi>wife</hi> be ill:</l>
                        <l>Ranke not in mariage with too high a blood</l>
                        <l>Lest with her birth she chance to twitt <hi>thee</hi> still,</l>
                        <l>Equalitie hath euer firmest stoode,</l>
                        <l>Where if <hi>descent</hi> of different order be</l>
                        <l>It's seldome sene that th'parties do agree.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one that's wise, yet to herselfe not so,</l>
                        <l>Louing to all, familiar to few</l>
                        <l>Inwardly faire, though meane in outward show,</l>
                        <l>Seldom conuersing in a publique vew;</l>
                        <l>Nor yong nor old, but has of yeares enow</l>
                        <l>To know vvhat huswife meanes, &amp; such an one</l>
                        <l>As may supplie thy place whē th'art from home.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one that like a Bosome-friend can keepe</l>
                        <l>Th'imparting of a secret, yet before</l>
                        <l>Thou dost commit to <hi>her</hi> matters more deepe</l>
                        <l>And consequent, thy iudgement should explore</l>
                        <l>And sound <hi>her disposition,</hi> so mai'st reape</l>
                        <l>What thou expectst: for if thou find a power</l>
                        <l>Apt to conceale, make her thy <hi>counsellour.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whose Spirit's ready to receaue</l>
                        <l>Impression of remorce for others grieues,</l>
                        <l>For <hi>such,</hi> best tempered natures euer haue</l>
                        <l>(And kind is <hi>she</hi> that others vvoes relieues)</l>
                        <l>Let her be open-hand'd to such as craue</l>
                        <l>If they be needie, for thou neuer heard</l>
                        <l>Almes (in charitie) lose her reward.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:8"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whose <hi>Education</hi> is <hi>more</hi> good</l>
                        <l>Then curious, whose life's more approu'd</l>
                        <l>Then noted, <hi>chuse</hi> one vvhose Parentall blood</l>
                        <l>Makes claime to vertue and is more belou'd</l>
                        <l>For her more choicer parts, then to be wo'ed</l>
                        <l>To an vnchaster motion, being inclin'd</l>
                        <l>To prize her bodies Beautie by <hi>her</hi> mind.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one vvhose knowing <hi>Parents</hi> can augment</l>
                        <l>Their daughters portion by a firme aduise,</l>
                        <l>One who will measure her's by thy content,</l>
                        <l>Whose spotlesse thoghts be vvritten in her eyes,</l>
                        <l>Whose Brest is thine clos'd in one <hi>Continent,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who know's <hi>yet seemes</hi> as if <hi>she</hi> did not know,</l>
                        <l>Inwardly good vvithout an outward show.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one who can play <hi>Mother,</hi> ere she haue</l>
                        <l>The name of <hi>Mother,</hi> one that hates nought more</l>
                        <l>Then not to learne, one that imprints her <hi>graue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Still in her memory, addes to thy store</l>
                        <l>With an aduised providence, nor doth craue</l>
                        <l>More of internall knowledg then to try</l>
                        <l>Her selfe on earth, and study how to <hi>die.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one who makes it greatest of her feare</l>
                        <l>T'incurre suspicion, that esteemes her name</l>
                        <l>Before a world of Treasure, that can beare</l>
                        <l>Affliction with indifference, and thinks <hi>shame</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>A Matrons comliest habit, one that's deare</l>
                        <l>In her <hi>Creators</hi> sight, and feares to do</l>
                        <l>Ought that <hi>thy selfe</hi> will not assent vnto.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:9"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one who doth desire to make each day</l>
                        <l>Her lifes <hi>Ephemeris,</hi> summing in th' euening tide</l>
                        <l>VVith what respect she past her howres away;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one that doates not on the name of <hi>Bride</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>VVith a new fangle itching, but will stay</l>
                        <l>To reason what it meanes, and is afraid</l>
                        <l>(In modest shame) to loose the stile of <hi>Maid.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one who's qualifide better in minde</l>
                        <l>Then Bodie: yet if she affect the straine</l>
                        <l>Of harmelesse <hi>chamber-musique,</hi> let her finde</l>
                        <l>Thy minde in consort with her, (for thogh vaine)</l>
                        <l>Yet 'tis an easie vanitie, and vnkinde</l>
                        <l>Mightst thou be deemd to bar her that delight,</l>
                        <l>Which may be shown euen in an Angels sight.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whose count'nance promiseth respect</l>
                        <l>Vnto her honour: one that spends the morne</l>
                        <l>In praying, not in painting, whose neglect</l>
                        <l>Is in <hi>out-landish</hi> fashions, and doth scorne</l>
                        <l>To fancie that which lightnesse doth affect:</l>
                        <l>One whose liues pattern rests as vncontrold,</l>
                        <l>And makes her <hi>Youth</hi> by imitation <hi>old.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whose house hath no affinitie</l>
                        <l>With follie, lust, ambition, selfe-conceit,</l>
                        <l>Prophanenesse, discord, prodigalitie,</l>
                        <l>Schisme, Superstition, violence, deceit,</l>
                        <l>Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ression, s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rfets, damned vsurie,</l>
                        <l>For where these raigne <hi>(my Son)</hi> we seldome see</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Descent of state vnto the third degree.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:9"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whō thou canst loue, not for constraint</l>
                        <l>Of fortune or of friends, for what are these</l>
                        <l>That thou by them shouldst measure thy content?</l>
                        <l>No, No, in mariage thou thy selfe must please,</l>
                        <l>Or euery day will be an argument</l>
                        <l>Of thy succeeding sorrow, then be wise,</l>
                        <l>Carue for thy selfe, yet heare thy friends aduise.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whose free election can admit</l>
                        <l>None saue thy selfe that she can dearely loue,</l>
                        <l>Yet so discreet as she can silence it</l>
                        <l>Till th'time her <hi>Parents</hi> shall her choice approue,</l>
                        <l>(For that implies her modestie and wit)</l>
                        <l>Where rash assents whens'euer they doe come,</l>
                        <l>Are euer seene to bring <hi>Repentance</hi> home.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse</hi> one whose <hi>Conscience</hi> and religion meet</l>
                        <l>In one set concord with thee, for it's this</l>
                        <l>That cements minds together, and makes sweet</l>
                        <l>Th' vnseasonedst passions, giuing way to blisse</l>
                        <l>And future glory, where the peacefull seat</l>
                        <l>Of two distinct mindes now reduc'd to one,</l>
                        <l>Shews equall temper both in mirth and mone.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chuse amongst these</hi> thou canst not <hi>Chuse amisse,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For here's a full variety of <hi>such</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Will fit thy mind as thou thy self wouldst wish,</l>
                        <l>Yet <hi>(Sonne)</hi> attempt not with vnhalowed tutch</l>
                        <l>To taint their honour with a wanton kisse,</l>
                        <l>For that is but inducement vnto sin,</l>
                        <l>Sith <hi>Kisses</hi> be the keieslet Treason in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:10"/>
                        <l>Therefore <hi>chuse one,</hi> and that but <hi>only one,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>One</hi> that may make two Bodies one-vnite,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>One</hi> that is essence-lesse if left alone</l>
                        <l>VVithout her second; <hi>One</hi> whose sole delight</l>
                        <l>Is vanisht when her second soule is gone:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>One</hi> that renewes her comfort in her <hi>make,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And ioyes in her <hi>affliction</hi> for <hi>his</hi> sake.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet know <hi>(my son)</hi> when thou this <hi>wife</hi> dost <hi>chuse,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And (after sute) art master of thy <hi>choise,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>It's fit thou should this louely <hi>mirror</hi> vse</l>
                        <l>VVith that respect as she may hence reioice</l>
                        <l>To haue a <hi>mate</hi> so rightly generouse.</l>
                        <l>As with a <hi>Wiues-choise therefore I begun,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Il'e shew what by a Husband should be don.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may command, yet should not tyrannize,</l>
                        <l>Shew himselfe <hi>head,</hi> yet not to make his <hi>wife</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His foot, esteeme her as his only prize,</l>
                        <l>(All other Blanks) hate all intestine strife</l>
                        <l>(Saue strife in loue,) he should not exercise</l>
                        <l>The patience of his <hi>wife,</hi> for one may wrong</l>
                        <l>Silence too much, and force her haue a tongue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may expresse his loue with modestie,</l>
                        <l>Yet neuer coll and kisse in open place,</l>
                        <l>For I should deeme such loue hypocrisie</l>
                        <l>Or some such thing, if I were in her case;</l>
                        <l>And better is loue showne in priuacie</l>
                        <l>Then 'fore the eies of men, for they will skan</l>
                        <l>Fondnesse or indiscretion in the <hi>man.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:10"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may be free in loue, for shee's his owne,</l>
                        <l>Yet such a loue as is exempt from staine</l>
                        <l>Of an insatiate lust: he should not frowne</l>
                        <l>T'expresse his aw too much, his best of gaine</l>
                        <l>Should be to make her vertues riper growne;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> should dispence with lighter faults, not vex</l>
                        <l>Himselfe for <hi>trifles,</hi> shee's the weaker sex:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may restraine her, but t'is not so good,</l>
                        <l>Restraint giues <hi>women</hi> greater appetite;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may doe much, but who would wrong his blood,</l>
                        <l>His <hi>flesh,</hi> himself? <hi>he</hi> may curb her delight,</l>
                        <l>But who knows not whē <hi>women's</hi> most with stood</l>
                        <l>Their wil's most forward &amp; their wits most neere thē,</l>
                        <l>And wil be <hi>frolike</hi> thogh their husbāds heare thē?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may haue care, but carking it is worse,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may be getting, yet <hi>he</hi> should not scrape;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> should not slaue himselfe vnto his purse,</l>
                        <l>But freely vse it for his credit sake:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> shold not wean his <hi>wife</hi> from ought by force,</l>
                        <l>But by perswasion: <hi>for deprau'd's her will,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That's only forc'd by violence from ill.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> may part stakes, or all, but it were better</l>
                        <l>To ioine in <hi>purse</hi> as they doe ioine in <hi>care,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Where each to other may remaine a debter,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For where the man doth limit th'Wife a share,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Oft turnes the Wife to be her husbands cheater,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which to preuent (if hee'le be sure of her)</l>
                        <l>In stake, state, store, make her his <hi>Treasurer.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:11"/>
                        <l>He may be Iealous; but't implies suspect</l>
                        <l>That <hi>he</hi> misdoubts what he <hi>himself</hi> hath bene,</l>
                        <l>Or that he's troubled with <hi>som weake defect</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His <hi>VVife</hi> perceaues, thogh to the world vnseene</l>
                        <l>And that from hence proceedeth her neglect</l>
                        <l>Of honour to his Bed: which (sure) would show</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Basenes</hi> in him, and force her to doe soe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He may picke cause and matter of offence</l>
                        <l>(But that would much degenerate from <hi>man</hi>)</l>
                        <l>He may heare <hi>such,</hi> as would sowe difference</l>
                        <l>Twixt their vnited loues; but if he scan</l>
                        <l>And rightly weigh <hi>mans</hi> natiue excellence,</l>
                        <l>He will conclude with this, that <hi>there is no man</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>So base, to vrge <hi>offence</hi> against a woman.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He may be busie <hi>where</hi> h'as nought to doe,</l>
                        <l>And intermedle in his <hi>wiues affayres,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But fit it is not that he should doe soe</l>
                        <l>For in employments <hi>ech</hi> haue distinct shares,</l>
                        <l>Nor she to <hi>his,</hi> nor he to <hi>hers</hi> should goe:</l>
                        <l>For so the <hi>Breeches</hi> she might seeme to weare,</l>
                        <l>And he a <hi>Coate-queanes</hi> name as rightlie beare.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He may thinke well on's <hi>wife,</hi> yet not commend</l>
                        <l>(For he doth praise <hi>himself,</hi> doth praise his wife):</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> should in life prepare him for his end</l>
                        <l>And mould his end by forming of his life:</l>
                        <l>He should repose no trust in anie friend</l>
                        <l>In or without him, saue in the firme defence</l>
                        <l>Of a resolu'd and spotlesse <hi>Conscience.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:11"/>
                        <l>Lastly he may (for it is in his power)</l>
                        <l>Now in his <hi>Exit,</hi> when he turnes to earth</l>
                        <l>To make his <hi>wife</hi> his sole <hi>Executour</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And by that meanes to <hi>begger</hi> all his birth,</l>
                        <l>But I should rather limit her a <hi>dower</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which might her ranke and order well befit,</l>
                        <l>For then so soone she will not <hi>him forget.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>These</hi> are the Cautions <hi>(Sonne)</hi> I'd haue thee keep,</l>
                        <l>Which well obseru'd wil crowne thy happy state,</l>
                        <l>Folding thy dull eyes in a cherefull sleepe,</l>
                        <l>Blessing thy fortune with a vertuous <hi>Mate;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Storing thy states content with such a heape</l>
                        <l>Of peacefull Treasure, as thou there shalt finde</l>
                        <l>Enough of wealth in thy contented minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Awake thee then, dull sleepe preuents thy <hi>Choice,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Here comes <hi>she</hi> whom thy fancy may approue,</l>
                        <l>Awake I say, and in thy Fate reioice</l>
                        <l>That thou hast met with such a modest <hi>Loue:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Come come, if thou in <hi>Reasons Scale</hi> wilt poize</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy selfe</hi> with <hi>her,</hi> thou wilt not curious be</l>
                        <l>But take good Fortune while it's offerd thee</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Awake, I vade: I wak'd, he vanished,</l>
                        <l>Where casting my amased eyes aside</l>
                        <l>Sent from the Recluse of a troubled head,</l>
                        <l>A modest bashfull virgin me espide,</l>
                        <l>Whom I approachd, being emboldened</l>
                        <l>By th'Apparition which assur'd no lesse</l>
                        <l>Vnto my hopes then honour and successe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:12"/>
                        <l>This Virgins name <hi>Simpliciana</hi> hight,</l>
                        <l>Daughter vnto <hi>Zelocto</hi> the precise,</l>
                        <l>Who had me once before discarded quite,</l>
                        <l>Because my weaker fortunes did not rise</l>
                        <l>To the hight of her expectance, yet that night</l>
                        <l>(So feruent is affection) did that <hi>Maide</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Trace me along to make her <hi>Loue</hi> displaide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Shame curb'd her tongue, yet fancy bad her speak,</l>
                        <l>While I suppli'd her silence with my speach,</l>
                        <l>And thus her passion for her selfe did break,</l>
                        <l>Whilst <hi>shee</hi> stood by and seconded the breach</l>
                        <l>With a teare-trickling eye and blushing cheeke,</l>
                        <l>Where thus I woo'd my selfe, yet in her name,</l>
                        <l>Shewing her loue, yet shadowing her shame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sir</hi> I doe loue you (thus I did begin)</l>
                        <l>I pray you make <hi>your selfe</hi> your Orator,</l>
                        <l>And so I did, yet taxe me not of sin</l>
                        <l>Or lightnesse, vnfain'd loue omits no houre</l>
                        <l>Though't be distemper'd, <hi>but will let him in</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Whom shee affecteth, for when all's' asleepe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Loues eies are said continuall watch to keepe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I haue a <hi>Mother</hi> Sir (and then she smil'd)</l>
                        <l>For well shee knew what I intend'd to speake,</l>
                        <l>Whom to obey i'me bound because her child,</l>
                        <l>Yet Reason tels me when we <hi>husbands</hi> seeke,</l>
                        <l>The stile of <hi>Parents</hi> is in part exil'd,</l>
                        <l>For we (by virgine-losse) lose our first name,</l>
                        <l>And as our <hi>husband's</hi> stil'd, wee're stil'd the same.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:12"/>
                        <l>What then though Riches please anothers eye,</l>
                        <l>My reason tels me there is <hi>something</hi> more</l>
                        <l>To consummate true ioy, then can relye</l>
                        <l>On outward fortunes, therefore <hi>once</hi> I swore,</l>
                        <l>And I will keepe my vow religiously,</l>
                        <l>If e're I wed (as halfe resolu'd I am)</l>
                        <l>It shall not be the <hi>substance</hi> but the <hi>Man.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yea, though I were oppos'd on either side,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>(My Father heere, my chiding Mother there)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet neither of their humors should deuide</l>
                        <l>My deerest Soule from <hi>her orbiculer,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For I doe know, though that my Mother chide,</l>
                        <l>My Father fret, and both stand chasing o're me,</l>
                        <l>I did but that <hi>themselues</hi> haue done before me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With that she broke her speech, with, S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. quoth she</l>
                        <l>You wooe well for your selfe, but I approue</l>
                        <l>What you haue spoke shall be confirm'd by me,</l>
                        <l>Nor shall my silent passion shrowd my loue,</l>
                        <l>For as thy shadow I will follow <hi>thee;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Where I assenting to what both had said,</l>
                        <l>Kist and clapt hands, &amp; so the <hi>match</hi> was made.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Now if you like our <hi>Match,</hi> giue vs our due</l>
                        <l>And bid your selues vnto our Nuptiall day,</l>
                        <l>Our best of <hi>welcome</hi> shall attend on you,</l>
                        <l>Yea, th' <hi>Bride</hi> herselfe (all nicenesse lay'd away)</l>
                        <l>Will meet you with a frollique game-some crue,</l>
                        <l>Where to your choice contents, &amp; <hi>Loues</hi> among,</l>
                        <l>Wee'le be as <hi>merry</hi> as the day is long.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But if (through some dogg'd humour) you'le not come,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Bride-groome saies, A Gods-name stay at home.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:13"/>
                     <head>The Authors choice.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>FAire</hi> may <hi>shee</hi> be, but not opinion'd <hi>so,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For that opinion euer lackies pride;</l>
                        <l>Louing to all, yet so as Man may know</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>She</hi> can reserue the proper name of <hi>Bride,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For weake is that Fort and easie is't to win</l>
                        <l>That makes a Breach for all to enter in.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I'de haue her face and blush to be her <hi>owne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For th'<hi>Blush</hi> which <hi>Art</hi> makes is <hi>adulterate,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Splene</hi> may <hi>she</hi> haue, yet wise to kepe it downe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Passion,</hi> yet <hi>Reason</hi> too to moderate:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Comely</hi> not gaudy: <hi>she</hi> &amp; none but <hi>shee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Wears the best <hi>cloathes</hi> that wears to her degree.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>To his <hi>5</hi> equally-affectionate Sisters all vertuous content.</head>
                     <l>TO you that are the chiefest of my care,</l>
                     <l>Tyes of my loue and figures of my life,</l>
                     <l>Send I this Character, where ech may share</l>
                     <l>Her equall portion in my <hi>rare-good Wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And be the Same, which I'me resolu'd you are:</l>
                     <l>So shall your Husbands say (I doubt it not.)</l>
                     <l>The Sisters liues prou'd what their Brother wrot.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours iointly as his owne, <hi>MVSOPHILVS</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:13"/>
                     <head>Ʋpon the Married Life.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>HAppy state,</hi> yet'las how few</l>
                        <l>Thinke them happy in their choice,</l>
                        <l>When they shun whom they did sue,</l>
                        <l>And in loath'd delights reioice;</l>
                        <l>Loath'd though lou'd, since they are growne</l>
                        <l>To loue <hi>others,</hi> loath their <hi>owne?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But who marries to impart</l>
                        <l>Selfe and substance to his wife,</l>
                        <l>Ioining with his <hi>hand</hi> his <hi>hart,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Onely gaines this blisse of life,</l>
                        <l>Yea to him is solely giuen</l>
                        <l>To thinke <hi>Earth</hi> a kinde of <hi>Heauen.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Happy then or haplesse most,</l>
                        <l>For of all, <hi>this</hi> hath no <hi>meane,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Losing least or euer lost,</l>
                        <l>Being still in her extreame;</l>
                        <l>Good if vs'd; abused, ill,</l>
                        <l>Onely well where there's one <hi>will.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:14"/>
                     <head>Vpon the single Life.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>THis</hi> by times-distempers fed,</l>
                        <l>Feeles <hi>vertigo</hi> in his head,</l>
                        <l>Euer wooing, neuer sped;</l>
                        <l>Lou'd he liues, if loathed, dead,</l>
                        <l>So as nought but doubts and feares,</l>
                        <l>Buz like hornets in his eares.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Care</hi> he needs not, yet's his care</l>
                        <l>More in that he needeth lesse,</l>
                        <l>Ayming to haue <hi>one</hi> may share</l>
                        <l>With <hi>him</hi> in his bale and blesse;</l>
                        <l>Gad he would yet knowes not where,</l>
                        <l>Wandring Starre-like heere and there.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Care</hi> who loues then, let him liue</l>
                        <l>Single; whereas such neede lesse,</l>
                        <l>As themselues to marriage giue,</l>
                        <l>For these want what they possesse:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Care</hi> whereof breedes now and then</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Broken sleepes</hi> in many men.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus choice breeds care,</hi> He <hi>only may reioice,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who ha's shak't hands with</hi> care <hi>and ta'ne his</hi> choice.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:14"/>
                  <p>REMAINS after Death:</p>
                  <p>Including by way of introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction diuers memorable obseruances occasioned vpon discourse of EPITAPHS and <hi>Epycedes;</hi> their distinction and definition seconded by appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Authors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>ANNEXED THERE BE diuers select <hi>Epitaphs</hi> and <hi>Hearce-attending Epods</hi> worthie our obseruation: The one describing what they were which now are not: The other comparing such as now are with those that were.</p>
                  <q>Dignum laude virum musa vetat mori.</q>
                  <p>MVSOPHILVS.</p>
                  <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by IOHN BEALE 1618.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:15"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:15"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may be obiected (Reader) that small is the concurrence, lesse the coherence in the titles of these two Subiects, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santly concluding that it were pittie; Death should so soone seaze on a good-wife by the course of nature, as shee is had heere in pursuit by <hi>Deaths remainder.</hi> But this obiection may be answered by a twofold solution: First, the Printers importunacie, whose desire was in regard of the breuitie of the former part, to haue it by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion of some other proper Subiect enlarged; to whose reasonable demand I equally condescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Secondly, the Subiects propriety, which, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer by the iudgement of the Critik censurer traduced (the pitch of whose knowledge aimes rather at taxing then teaching) concurres as well with the precedent Title, as Man with mortalitie, Time with mutabilitie, Life with death. And as the more vertuous the neerer ofttimes their disso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which no doubt proceedes from Gods mercy
<pb facs="tcp:178199:16"/> that they might haue of him a fuller contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; so we commonly see the best Wiues limited to the shortest times, approued by that Maxime:
<q>
                        <l>For this each daies experience seemes to show</l>
                        <l>Ill wiues liue longer farre then good ones doe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let this suffice: if not, let the Subiect it selfe sleight his censure, whose singu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie makes of each thing an error.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>MVSOPHILVS.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:16"/>
                  <head>OBSERVATIONS VPON <hi>Epitaphs:</hi> their Antiquitie and vse; with Authoritie from approued Authors of their deriuations; with diuers other memorable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currences.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the memory of the dead consists vpon the life of the liuing: so their vertues or vices giue testimony of the dead, whether worthy the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the liuing, or to be buried in eternall obliuion? For this cause are Epitaphs (and euer haue beene) engrauen vpon the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Tombes and Sepulchers of the dead, either to expresse their fame, or by modest silencing what they were, to intimate how their actions li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, deserued no great memory dying. Some I distinguish (Epitaphs I meane) of this nature, in to Morall, others into Diuine, and other is pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phane. Morall (to giue instances in each ki<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> be such as include a morall or excellent vse <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:17"/> made by the liuing of the Actions of the dead, by recourse had to their Monuments, where mortalitie is not onely liuely expressed, but their conditions fully and amply charactred. Such were the <hi>Epitaphs</hi> of <hi>Cyrus, Semiramis, Laomedon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is recorded<note n="a" place="margin">Vide Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Curtium in Sup. &amp; vit. Cyr.</note> when <hi>Alexander</hi> that great Monarch of the World came into <hi>Persia,</hi> and there chanced to see the famous Tombe of <hi>Cyrus</hi> whereon was engrauen this Epitaph or inscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Whosoeuer thou be, or whencesoeuer thou shalt come and beholdest this Tombe, know that I am</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, <hi>who translated the Empire from the</hi> Medes <hi>to the</hi> Persians: <hi>pray thee do not enuie me, for this little clod of earth that doth couer me. Alexander</hi> (I say) see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this inscription, could not containe himselfe from teares: making (without all question) this morall vse of it: That Princes (though neuer so potent or eminent, so victorious or puissant) but becomes subiect to the common doome and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of Fate, and must of necessitie leaue all their conquests and victories (by a forced surrender) to the ineuitable command of death. So as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> when he beheld the Tombe of <hi>Achilles,</hi> cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>Felix es, qui talem laudum tuarum praeconem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>abuisti (nempe Homerum:)</hi> so heere he wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erly, saying, <hi>Infelix es Cyre qui tantis victorijs <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>clytus extitisti, tamen à morte te vinci patieris.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> reade (that I may goe forward in prosecution instances of this nature:) That <hi>Cyrus</hi> (also)
<pb facs="tcp:178199:17"/> when he beheld the Tombe of that memorable Queene <hi>Semyramis,</hi> and saw this to be writ vpon it: <hi>Whosoeuer shall digge vp this stone which now doth couer me, shall finde an infinite masse of treasure vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it,</hi> commanded the same to be taken vp; which being done (in stead of Treasure) he found this morall vnder it; <hi>None but misers (or godlesse persons) would digge vp the Graues of the dead.</hi> An excellent caution for the couetous wretch, who is euer catching by hooke or crooke, <hi>Quo iure, qua{que} iniuria, per fas nefasve;</hi> not regarding the meanes, so he may attaine the end; nor respecting pietie nor common humanitie, publique causes or Countries benefit, so he may please his vnsatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied desires. But this violation of the dead, this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury done against those who sleepe in peace, hath been euen by the Pagans themselues esteemed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable: so as the<note n="b" place="margin">In the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of <hi>Asia</hi> and <hi>Affr.</hi> vid. Egypt Solem. Funer.</note> Aegyptians are interred with their best gems, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, and Iewels: which (so strickt be their Lawes in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect) are neuer embezeled, but remaine with them; hoping (saith the Historian) that their substance will deliuer them, if any punishment or vnworthy censure should be inflicted on them. The tombe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of that perfidious Prince (<note n="c" place="margin">Vide Homer. eleg. sanè. Graecorum: Odyssea errorum, Ilias Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, &amp;c.</note>
                     <hi>Laomedon</hi>) had this Epitaph:
<q>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:18"/>
                        <l>Qui cum Hoste fidem fefellit</l>
                        <l>Cum morte fidem seruauit.</l>
                     </q> The morall thus expressed: When <hi>Hercules</hi> (in the deliuery of Troy from that deuouring mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, a Whale; and in the rescuing of <hi>Laomedons</hi> faire daughter <hi>Hesyone,</hi> should by couenant haue receiued two milk-white steeds: the king retiring to his (miserable Troy) commanded the gates of the Citie to be shut against him; infringing his faith and promise; which so incensed the ire and indignation of <hi>Hercules</hi> against him, as within few yeares his Citie was sacked and demolished, his Subiects captiued, his daughter to <hi>Telamon</hi> es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poused; and himselfe (to extinguish the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ingratitude, fully to appeale the enraged furie of <hi>Hercules,</hi> was slaughtered. Whose mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument was reserued (as a perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of perfidious dealing to his posterity, with the inscription aboue mentioned.</p>
                  <p>Tombes<note n="d" place="margin">The entiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Tombes.</note> haue beene aunciently vsed; as wee may reade in sacred writ: where one Sepulcher was kept solemnly for a whole familie, euery one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning in <hi>Sepulchra maiorum:</hi> but neuer so sump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous before the erection of that memorable Tombe (or Shrine rather) of Prince <hi>Mausolus</hi> king of Caria: whose Queene <hi>Artemisia</hi> erected such a gorgeous Tombe in his memory, as all Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers since (especially of Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours
<pb facs="tcp:178199:18"/> and Carian Princes) are called to this day <hi>Mausolea:</hi> the inscription this,
<q>
                        <l>Si te non teneat, tumulum struet ossa tenere,</l>
                        <l>Quem tibi defuncto coniugis optat amor.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Two monuments we reade of to be famous, in that their erection was the foundation of many potent and puissant people: some also were taken for preseruers of that Region wherein they were planted and seated: as the<note n="e" place="margin">Two aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Monuments which were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Asyla pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triae &amp;c.</note> Tombe or Sepulcher of <hi>Aiax</hi> in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian shore: and the Tombe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles</hi> in Sygaeum: Which two, euen to this day continue memorable: so as in the greatest depopulations and sackings of Cities, the ruinating of their Forts and Castles of defence, they were euer kept vntouched (as shrines and monuments inuiolate, obelisks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrate, or statues deified: supposing (in their owne blindnesse deceiued) that their preseruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was deriued from them.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed in <hi>Epitaphs</hi> (on which our dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course doth principally consist:) they are deriued from the Greeke<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> &amp; signifie as much as an inscriptiō, or any thing which is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced or fixed vpon the Tombe (<hi>Quae in scitis &amp; scu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quorundam Regum vidimus</hi> saith <hi>Lipsius:</hi>) as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pycedion</hi> (deriued from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>lugubria ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere</hi>) are writ before or after the corps interred, but not vpon the Tombe: being more dilated
<pb facs="tcp:178199:19"/> measures, either expressing the memorable acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his life (or if nothing worthy in his life) at least modestly to shut vp his desertlesse life, with a commemoration of humane frailty: silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the person, lest his description should mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster either matter of offence or assentation: of <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> if truely expressed; of <hi>assentation,</hi> if aboue merit praised. Hee that neither benefited him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe nor his Countrie; (but, <hi>vt Canis in presepi</hi>) was rightly demonstrated with this <hi>Impressa, Hic Vir diu fuit:</hi> This man was long, but liued not long: for life and being haue an essentiall diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. We are said to liue when we expresse our life by externall effects, knowing for what wee were ordained; for what borne; not to retire our selues from publique affaires, for priuate ease: but to further our Countrie, and propagate her glory by serious and vigilant managements, both at home and abroad. This man is said to liue, that hath left some monument or testimonie behinde him that he liued.</p>
                  <p>We are only said to be, when we only breathe, respectles of either publique or priuate: imitating those Flies <hi>Ephemerae,</hi> which flicker a little with their wings (limiting their life within one day) &amp; presently die. These as the Philosopher saith, <hi>spirant tantùm non viuunt.</hi> But too much of them, both die: Yet this is the difference: the one dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, leaueth a testimony behinde him that hee once liued; The other being dead, hath no
<pb facs="tcp:178199:19"/> hope that his memory shall euer bee reuiued.</p>
                  <p>Many pretie <hi>Epitaphs</hi> the Romanes vsed; briefe, yet ample enough to describe the nature of the person whom they would haue memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Virgil</hi> writing on one <hi>Balista</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Jn vit. Nar. &amp; frag.</note> (a great sword and buckler-man) as I may terme him, frequenting places of aduantage, to rob, and surprise passengers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares, cheeres the poore way-faring-man with this comfortable inscription on <hi>Balistas</hi> graue:
<q>
                        <l>Who ere he be that passeth by this way,<note place="margin">Monte sub hoc laepidum teg. &amp;c.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>May safely trauell both by night and day,</l>
                        <l>And that he may confirme it with his eies,</l>
                        <l>Vnder this heape of stones <hi>Balista</hi> lies,</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Or thus,
<q>
                        <l>Since the time <hi>Balista</hi> heere interred was,</l>
                        <l>Or day or night the Traueller may passe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that vpon his Flie or Gnat:
<q>
                        <l>Heere I expresse what thou once did to mee,</l>
                        <l>Solemnizing thy death to honour thee.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that of <hi>Sylenus</hi> the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Swaine:
<q>
                        <l>Vnder this tuft of wood lies there a Swaine,</l>
                        <l>Came drunke to Earth, went drunke to Earth againe:</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:20"/>
                  <p>And that of <hi>Minos</hi> king of Crete
<q>
                        <l>Heere <hi>Minos</hi> lies who plai'd the Iudge so well</l>
                        <l>On Earth, that now hee's made a Iudge in Hell.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Minos</hi> for his excellent iudgement and iustice in Crete, being seuere, and therefore his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute was rightly giuen him: he was said to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ough and seuere, exact and austere in all his censures: for which cause he was trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated from the principalitie of Crete, to the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Hell: (as Poets faine.)</p>
                  <p>In the discourse of arguments of this nature: as we haue many write <hi>Epitaphs</hi> (some panegyrick) in way of commendation and praise: others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectiue to expresse the merite or defect of any person: we should be warie heerein, lest either by vaine<note n="h" place="margin">Sicut lingua loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis proficit in aur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientis, ita calamus scribentis in oculo le gentis, &amp; ad interiora cordis peruenit sensus dirigentis, sicut verba instruentis: Albin. in praefatio: comment in Iohan.</note> &amp; adulatorie praise, we giue error a warrant, or by too detractiue inuection, wee seeme (<hi>grauius in sepulchra mortuorum calcare,</hi> that I may vse the Philosophers saying. But to omit the vse of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphs,</hi> which of themselues haue euer ministred occasion of imitation or detestation: I will proceede to the antiquitie of <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> and afterward descend to the seuerall branches which I haue before in my methode to my selfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epitaphs</hi> haue bene euer vsed vpon the <hi>Tombes</hi> of the deceased, to express their Vertues or vices. Of all the seuen<note n="i" place="margin">Vide La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert. de vit. philoso.</note> Sages of Greece, not one there is, but charactred to the ful by their especiall appropriates: and though diuers (in contempt of vaine glory or ostentation) haue precisely commanded vpō their death-beds, that no statue, shrine, nor inscription should be erected or engrauen in their memories: yet so gratefull was posteritie to so noble pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors, as they would in no wise suffer so Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant exploits either publique or priuate, to bee buried in silence and obliuion. Yea euer in those times, where <hi>fines imperij tueri magis, quàm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, mos erat:</hi> as in those Golden times, and empires of <hi>Vexores</hi> King of Aegypt, and <hi>Tanais</hi> King of Scythia which Historians take to be the first Monarchs and sole Gouernours in the world; euen thē (I say) were <hi>Epitaphs</hi> of this nature verie frequent, and common: and in <hi>Ninus</hi> time, who succeeded, or rather dissolued their gouernment, we reade <hi>Epitaphs</hi> euen written vpon his Tombe; describing his nature and disposition at large, the manner of his discipline in warre, the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his Empire or Gouernment, and the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of his death.</p>
                  <p>To speake of the effeminate Gouernment and principality of the Amazons (women of incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and incredible fortune, valour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution) wee haue yet those Tombes and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers
<pb facs="tcp:178199:21"/> of the<note n="k" place="margin">Tumuli Amazo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> Amazons celebrated to this day amongst those Pagans, for the infinite numbers slaine by <hi>Hercules,</hi> in his inuasion of Amazon: where the worthie exploits of those (more then women) for their discipline and experience in warres, are in golden Characters registred and recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
                  <p>We reade euen in those (who for their magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitie and resolution) were termed <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>Heroes,</hi> men of heroicke dispositiō, to haue had in former times inscriptions vpon their Graues and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, to expresse what they were liuing, that deserued so exceeding commendation dying. Such were <hi>Alcides, Theseus, Hector, Perithous,</hi> and the renowne of <hi>Greece</hi> (the auncient <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troclus,</hi>) vpon whose graue whilst <hi>Achilles</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he imagined true valour to be charactred on his Graue, and a sufficient occasion of exciting and instigating the vnworthiest and vnresoluedst spirits to take in hand managements of greatest difficulty.</p>
                  <p>We reade of <hi>Tarina</hi> Queene of <hi>Saca,</hi> that she was no lesse memorable for her sepulcher, (sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing both in bountie &amp; specious edifice, then the Pyramides of Aegipt; Labyrinth in Crete, cō<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triued and inuented by <hi>Dedalus,</hi> or that sumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Monument erected by <hi>Artemisia</hi> in honour of her husband <hi>Mansolus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we should descend to the Persian Princes
<pb facs="tcp:178199:21"/> elected after the (premature death of<note n="p" place="margin">Gladio sua sponte euaginato grauiter vulneratus occubuit Iust <hi>1.</hi> lib:</note>
                     <hi>Cambyses</hi>) wee shall there more eminently surueigh the processe of their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and their ends (some with glorie and renowne) others with no lesse infamie and reproch attaind.</p>
                  <p>Yet to vse decencie in the celebration of fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rites and solemnities: for I know (that I may vse the morallists opinion) there is a vaine-glorie euen in death; and as the pompe of death doth more terrifie then death it selfe, so doth the pompe of death more excite men to die willingly then their expectance after death. For this all the <hi>Romaine</hi> Emperours would haue their Tombes erected in their life time, with all externall osten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and popularitie: to intimate a kind of Empire euen in death: which may appeare by that (which <hi>Suetonius</hi> speakes in the life of <hi>Augustus</hi>) that before his death, the statue which was erected and set vp in his memorie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing strucken with Thunder, lost the first letter of his Name (to wit C.) which signified as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurs diuined, that within a hundred daies imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatelie following, he should depart the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cato</hi> in dede (who tooke it <hi>nobile lethum</hi> to die for his countrie and the preseruation of her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie) would haue no shrine, statue, nor inscriptiō set vp in his memory; supposing his vertues to be sufficient annals and records to eternise his name.</p>
                  <p>Of this minde was <hi>Phocion</hi> the Athenian (both
<pb facs="tcp:178199:22"/> Stoicks for their discipline) seeming vnwilling to imitate the popular in exterior rites: being (as they deemed) able to expresse their owne liues by their deaths, their deaths by their liues. Which may be the cause which moued <hi>Flaccus</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne all monuments, with this resolued securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>Vnde mihi lapidem &amp;c.</hi> What auailes it to haue Monuments, Stones, Shrines or Statues to memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise Vs? what skils it to haue labels hung vpon our Sepulchers (as those siluer swords of Greece ouer the Sepulcher of <hi>Philip;</hi> those golden Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Persia ouer the memorable tombe of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes?</hi> as the same Poet saith, —<hi>Non datur emis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so reditus tibi</hi>— It is true: yet so respectiue should man be of the demerited &amp; praise-worthy acts of his Ancestors (so superstitiously careful that their monuments be not in obliuion smothered) as no time should be omitted (wherein we may as the Orator saith, <hi>defunctorum memoriae seruire</hi>) but with all instance to perfect &amp; accōplish the same.</p>
                  <p>We<note n="m" place="margin">Vid. descr. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fric. Qui sepulcra maiorum vt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria domicilia la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resque existima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note> reade that the Pagans haue been so respectiue hereof, that the monumēts of their parents &amp; kins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes haue been no lesse deare to them, then their own houses, their owne habitations and dwellings: Esteeming their reputation (to be purchased) by the purchase of their Auncestors glory, and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the preseruation of their memory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Agathocles</hi> Prince of Syracuse (willing to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb facs="tcp:178199:22"/> a Monument or Statue in his owne memory, to expresse humane frailtie) commanded that the head and vpper parts should be made of solid gold, but the feete of earth; with this Impresse: <hi>Sic omnia firma.</hi> An excellent obseruation and caution to put Man in minde of his substance and subsistence, constitution and dissolution: that standing on no firmer feete then earth, no stronger arches (then staies of mortality) he should euer feare lest so proud a building should fall, being supported by so vnstable and vnable props.</p>
                  <p>But for Antiquitie (as shee is said to be the warrant of things done, the confirmer of things present, and president of things to come; so oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vices haue beene bolstered by her, impieties authorized by her, and a direction to greater laid open by her. I will descend therefore briefely to particularize such <hi>Epitaphs</hi> (vsed by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents) which remained for caueats or obseruations in succeeding times. As others (likewise) that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and excited men to vndertake valiant and couragious exploits in hand.</p>
                  <p>We reade that <hi>Augustus</hi> (when he died at <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> being a Towne seated in the middle part of <hi>Campania</hi>) his souldiers to expresse and manifest their loue to him dying, as they had done their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance to him liuing, burst out in seuerall passi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of sorrow, griefe, and pensiue distractions, with these speeches: <hi>O God, that he had either ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene borne, or that he had neuer died: For the
<pb facs="tcp:178199:23"/> one</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Alterum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim pessimi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepti, exitus praeclari alterū &amp;c.</note>
                     <hi>is an occasion of our misery, the other a president of his glory.</hi> For so great was his loue towards the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, that by his owne care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, he commanded great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of graine to be brought out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> to sustaine his people welnie consumed with famine.</p>
                  <p>Few of the twelue Romane Emperors reade we so excellent and exquisite commendations of: saue <hi>Titus,</hi> who receiued this Impresse euen vpon his hearse, to be <hi>Amor &amp; deliciae generis humani:</hi> Mans darling, the Worlds mirror, and the flower of all Romane Emperors either before or since; being directed and enlightned no further then with the beameling of nature. For to recapitulate the natures of all those Princes, twixt <hi>Augustus</hi> the first of the twelue (saue one) to <hi>Titus,</hi> the last of the twelue, saue one, we shall see their dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions variable, inconstant, dissolute, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally vicious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tiberius</hi> taxed for his subtiltie, <hi>Caligula</hi> for his insolencie, <hi>Claudus</hi> for his effeminacie, <hi>Nero</hi> for his cruelty, <hi>Galba</hi> for his intemperancie, <hi>Oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Vita omnis tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, maxime ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lescentia &amp;c. vid. Sext. Aurel. de Oth.</note> for his inhumanitie, <hi>Vitellius</hi> for his prodigalitie, <hi>Ʋespasian</hi> for his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery: These haue wee charactred (which the Romane Annals haue expressed to life) such as either merited eternall infamie by their vicious gouernment, or due commendation for
<pb facs="tcp:178199:23"/> their many morall vertues wherewith they were endued and inuested. <hi>Vita mortuorum est in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria viuentium</hi> (saith one very well:) for it renues and reuiues the memory of the dead, and makes him liue in name, honour and reputation, when the sithe of Fate hath pruned him.</p>
                  <p>For this all the Romane Emperors haue labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, desiring to become memorable after death: <hi>Curtius</hi> throwing himselfe into the lake; <hi>Vtican</hi> purchasing his liberty by voluntary death; <hi>Hora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Cocles</hi> throwing himselfe violently into <hi>Tyber</hi> to preserue his Countries libertie;<note n="r" place="margin">In capite eius veluti cornua e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merse runt &amp;c. Valer. Max. lib.</note>
                     <hi>Genitius Cippus</hi> subiecting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe to death to propagate his Countries glory; <hi>P. Decius</hi> who rushed into the fore-front of the enemies (encountring a whole Armie) to make his owne memory more famous and illustrious: The like of <hi>Scipio Affricane,</hi> who to extinguish that menacing fire of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> deuoted himselfe to death for the safegard of his Country. These and many more, who illustrated their Names by atchieuements done liuing, expected (without question) no little celebration of their name and memory dying: and though their opinion rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched not to the soules immortality; yet they could extend their imaginations thus farre, as a famous and memorable death surpassed an infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and ignominious life: wishing rather to die in fame, then liue in eternall obscurity. Which
<pb facs="tcp:178199:24"/> caused some (of disposition vnequall to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) to perpetrate some hainous and enormious crime, whereby they might purchase fame euen by infamie: Such was <hi>Herostratus</hi> who burned the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Ephesus,</hi> to purchase him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a name. Such was <hi>Turulius</hi> who hewed downe the graue that was consecrate to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Aesculapius,</hi> to erect him a ship, that once Religion (as he himselfe auowed) might ride on the water: And such was <hi>Q. Fuluius</hi> who to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich himselfe (by sinister meanes) tooke from the Temple dedicated to <hi>Iuno Lucinia, tegulas quas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam marmoreas,</hi> for which he sustained condigne punishment; amongst which we may insert that sacrilegious Prince or Tyrant rather (for his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of <hi>Syracuse</hi> as it came vnto him by an vsur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped succession, so it was gouerned by as cruell and tyrannicall a disposition) bearding the Gods, and afterwards robbing the Altars and Temples (of their sacred ornaments.) For coming one day to the Temple of <hi>Iupiter Olympius,</hi> and seeing his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage gloriously beautified with a<note n="q" place="margin">Quo eum Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannus Hiero &amp;c. manubijs Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giniens. ornauerat &amp;c.</note> vestment of gold (of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding weight and inestimable price) commanded it to be taken from him, and a woollen garment to be giuen him in the stead of it: saying, <hi>A coate of gold was too heauy for him in Summer, too cold in Winter; but a woollen garment was fitter for both seasons.</hi> Many of these haue we
<pb facs="tcp:178199:24"/> recorded by Historians, whose liues were no lesse prophane, then their ends miserable.</p>
                  <p>Vpon all which (if we might insist vpon this argument) <hi>Epitaphs</hi> very answerable to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and despicable liues might be produced. But we must proceed, because this summarie dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, (which I haue heere placed and prefixed (as a preamble or fore-runner) to our <hi>Epitaphs</hi> following) is but intended onely to demonstrate the vse and effect of <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> with their first in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, &amp; their distinct kinds arising from their primarie vses.</p>
                  <p>It is true that there is no necessitie in Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, or specious monuments; for <hi>coelo tegitur, qui non habet vrnam:</hi> which moued <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Cynick to bid his friends cast his body vnto the dogges when he was dead: and being answered by them, that the dogges would teare and rent it: Set a staffe by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e (quoth he) and I wil beate them from it. Yet in this seeming contempt of buriall, we shall reade in most of the liues of the Pagans, that they were respectiue where they should be interred, erecting (as in part hath beene mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) very goodly and glorious Sepulchers in their life-times to eternise their memory after death: with whom (it fared many times) as it fared once with<note n="r" place="margin">Shebna sibi tumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la condit, quem fata negarunt.</note>
                     <hi>Shebna,</hi> who made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a Sepulcher in one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, but was buried in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">The first that bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried such as fell in warre.</note>
                     <hi>Hercules</hi> (we reade) to be the first that euer buried such as fell in warre. Many ancient <hi>Epitaphs</hi> we haue by transcription, engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon the monuments of the deceased: as in the Northerne parts especially, where in the very ruines of time, we may see some monumentall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription inserted, to reuiue the memory of the dead. As in the warres of the Saxons, Picts, and Danes: no coast being more frequent then the North, to expresse the memorable acts done in former time, as also to set out the very places and circumstances of things atchieued, with the manuscripts traduced from former occurrents e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to these present times: many curious and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Antiquaries hauing viewed and particularly set downe the especiallest records heereof with diuers memorable inscriptions happily occurring to their surueigh, I will ouerpasse the same, lest I should seeme to trifle out my time with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent discourse.</p>
                  <p>It is true that a Souldiers resolution euer fixed on braue attempts, and the inlarging of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries glory, should rather aime at fame after death, then to erect for himselfe a curious monument in his death: which moued <hi>Caesar</hi> in the plaine of <hi>Pharsalie</hi> to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,
<q>
                        <l>—<note n="t" place="margin">Sep. li. Lucan.</note> Capit omnia tellus</l>
                        <l>Quae genuit: coelo tegitur, qui non habet vrnam.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:25"/>
                  <p>And againe that martiall straine of valour:
<q>
                        <l>Nil agis hac ira, tabesne cadauera soluat,</l>
                        <l>An rogus, hand spectat: placido natura receptat cuncta sinu.</l>
                     </q> And so concludes the Declamour in <hi>Seneca:</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture giues euery man a graue: seconded by old <hi>Anchises</hi> resolution:
<q>Nec tumulum curo, sepelit natura relictos.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet humanitie requires these finall obsequies, not onely in remembrance of our dead friends, but euen to manifest the sinceritie of our loues, in erecting monuments ouer them dead, which might preserue their memory, and confirme our affections in their deaths.</p>
                  <p>The friends of <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> (surnamed <hi>Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat</hi>) seeing his much lamented end, desired much to expresse their loue vnto their dead friend; yet withall to conceale the infamie and reproach of his death: yet <hi>Callimachus</hi> plaied the Epigram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matist vpon his graue, whilest his deare friends deplored his vntimely end. The Epigram (inscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed after the forme of an <hi>Epitaph</hi>) being fixed on his Tombe, whence all <hi>Epitaphs</hi> haue their deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, was this,
<q>
                        <l>-Vita vale, muro praeceps delapsus ab alto</l>
                        <l>Dixisti moriens, <hi>Ambrociata</hi> puer,</l>
                        <l>-Nullū in morte malū credēs. sed scripta <hi>Platonis</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Non ita erant animo percitienda tuo.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:26"/>
                  <p>In English thus,
<q>
                        <l>The yong <hi>Ambrociat,</hi> whilst himselfe he threw</l>
                        <l>From off the wall, bad to his life adew,</l>
                        <l>Deeming (as <hi>Plato</hi> wrote) in death's no woe,</l>
                        <l>But he mistooke it: <hi>Plato</hi> meant not soe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>This booke which mooued <hi>Ambrociat</hi> to this precipitate attempt, is imagined to be <hi>Platoes Phaedo</hi> of the immortalitie of the soule: which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so (by a misconstruction) <hi>Cato Vtican</hi> apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, laid violent hand vpon himselfe, to free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe from the tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nie and illimited soueraignty of the vsurping <hi>Caesar.</hi> But to our argument pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</p>
                  <p>We haue shadowed briefely the first branch (or kinde which we proposed in the beginning) to wit, morall <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> being such as conduce to instruction either publike or priuate, wherein (by the very inscriptions or titles engrauen vpon the Tombes of the deceased) some haue beene moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to imitate their memorable liues in actions and attempts of like nature; as <hi>Caesar</hi> in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh of <hi>Mithridates, Augustus</hi> in the surueigh of <hi>Caesar, Alexander</hi> by the monument of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilles, Achilles</hi> by the fame-engrauen monument of <hi>Patroclus, Aenaeas</hi> by the renowned Tombe of the matchlesse<note n="u" place="margin">Andromach in Hom. called He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Troiae <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <hi>Hector,</hi> and <hi>Hector</hi> by the eternized memorie of <hi>Antenor:</hi> These were morall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing or exciting Impresses, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mindes of the beholders
<pb facs="tcp:178199:26"/> to the management of the like approued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted acts.</p>
                  <p>We will now proceede to <hi>Epitaphs</hi> (comming neerer a diuine composition) excellent for their graue and diuinely mouing sentences; pithy for their effect, and profitable for their vse.</p>
                  <p>That is an excellent one of <hi>Scaligers: Scalige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri quod reliquum est:</hi> and that no lesse diuine of <hi>Caius: Fui Caius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epitaphs</hi> of this kinde seeme little affectiue, yet include so exquisite a straine, as they may rightly be termed diuine: surpassing mortalitie in description of our mortality; they delineate the state of man, extenuate his pompe, and shew to what end man was created, not to be onely, but to liue: there being an essentiall difference (twixt being and liuing) as I haue before specifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. We haue some of these which set out vanity in her naturall colours: and imply diuinely, what they propound morally.</p>
                  <p>Diuers we reade of, that fearefull (it seemes) to commend the writing of their <hi>Epitaphs</hi> to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie, would euer be prouided of one in their owne time: which (to expresse their worth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) did not shew or character their worth, but in a modest silence describe their owne frailetie, shutting vp their fame and memory, with a fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to Earth and Vanitie. These be soueraigne cordials to cheere the drouping and deiected spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: such as liue iniuried by time, oppressed by
<pb facs="tcp:178199:27"/> greatnesse of enmity, and slaued to penurie: Such I say, as liue obscurely in the eye of the World, neither noted nor reputed.</p>
                  <p>When the rich-man seeth nothing vpon <hi>Croesus</hi> graue, but a <hi>Fui Croesus:</hi> nor the poore-man vpon <hi>Irus</hi> then, <hi>Fui Irus:</hi> what difference at their dissolution? though in the eye of vaine and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular accompts, there be a maine difference.</p>
                  <p>These diuine <hi>Epitaphs</hi> moue the intellectual part to an apprehension of humane condition; to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider that we are al made <hi>ex</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Homo ex humo. Terra à terendo. Cadauer à cadendo. Vèrmis quia inermis.</note>
                     <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem argilla:</hi> &amp; as no difference in frame &amp; module, so no differēce in the end and period; only that which was writ vpon the <hi>Bauarians</hi> graue shal ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirme our hopes, or make vs eternally mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable:—<hi>Sit comes intemerata fides:</hi> or that which was engrauen on the Tombe of a Venetian Lord:
<q>Qui<note n="x" place="margin">Quod Seneca in Vatiae tumulum scripsit. Hic situs est Vatia: dormire e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim magis quam viuere videbatur.</note> vixit, viuet, qui fuit, ille perit.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>One no lesse diuine then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, distinguishing betwixt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and liuing: where our actions must be poised, our intentions dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cussed, and the vniuersalitie of nature discoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red We are drawne by these <hi>Epitaphs</hi> to disua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the pompe and port of this World; lesse to pamper the inordinate and distempered affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Flesh: holding as the Platonists held, onely the Soule to be Man, and the body to be a
<pb facs="tcp:178199:27"/> case or couer to put it in: And as <hi>Seneca</hi> termes it, a rinde or barke: so to fixe onely the light and splendor of the internall part vpon that soueraign end, by which we may ende in glory, as we were borne in misery.</p>
                  <p>And miserable did the Philosopher account that man, whose best of memories consisted in faire &amp; eminent obsequies; vertue being the best shrine, the exquisitest monument which can be erected to honour man. How should we best de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe our selues, and the excellencie of our owne natures, but by the contempt of death, expresse our owne affections euen vpon our graues, shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our selues to be Christians?</p>
                  <p>The memorable inscriptions of the ancient Princes (who died in their Countries right) may excite vs to managements of no lesse cōsequence. The Inscription vpon<note n="y" place="margin">Qui pannosus sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta collo gerens, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stra hostium ingreditur. Iust. secundo lib.</note>
                     <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drus</hi> Tombe, who was Prince of <hi>Athens,</hi> was — <hi>Haec mors mihi nomen ademit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like we reade of <hi>Attilius Regulus,</hi> who rather then he would infringe his faith, willingly returned vnto his enemies the Carthaginians: where, after he had endured intollerable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and vnworthie of so great and equally dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed minde, he commanded this <hi>Epitaph</hi> to be engrauen vpon his obscure Tombe, <hi>Nec sine spe perij.</hi> Many such may we reade in the memorable Annals of the Romanes, specially in the warre
<pb facs="tcp:178199:28"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Carthage and Rome: in which warres, no man of esteeme or ennobled ranke died, that was not graced with some inscription vpon his monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Yet <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, whose prudence in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning, sinceritie in disposing, promptnesse in attempting, and firme resolution in seconding, got him an eternal fame, both at home &amp; abroad: abroad in following <hi>Scylla</hi> at home in bearing vp the main building of the State with his graue and discreete supportance: euen this <hi>Pompey</hi> had but a short <hi>Epitaph</hi> writ vpon him, <hi>Hîc situs est magnus.</hi> Heere lies the pompe of a puissant and potent <hi>Pompey:</hi> heere lies Romes <hi>Atlas,</hi> the Easterne terror, and his friends aduancer: one whom nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imminence of perill, nor mutation of state, nor occurrence in fate could alter or dismay: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that powerfull Columne is now ruined, his glory dazled, and the mansion which was made glorious by him in Rome, becomes reduced to a poore and homely Sepulcher in Aegypt.</p>
                  <p>One chancing to come where king <hi>Dennis</hi> was buried: being depriued of crowne and dignity by reason of his tyrannicke gouernment, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death had retired himselfe to a simple Schoole, where he taught scholers; saying, <hi>Et re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam inuitis fatis:</hi> vnderstanding the course and processe of his gouernment, writ this short <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph</hi> vpon his Tombe:
<q>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:28"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dennis</hi> eras, &amp; <hi>Dennis</hi> eris, nec rege minorem</l>
                        <l>Te tua fata vocant: Rexque Magister eris:</l>
                        <l>Rex populi crudelis eras, puerisque Magister</l>
                        <l>Saeuior, his celerem fata dedere finem.</l>
                        <l>Nec regis inuitis fatis, è culmine regni,</l>
                        <l>Vt cadis, admissum est deseruisse scholam.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In English thus,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dennis</hi> thou was, and <hi>Dennis</hi> thou shalt be,</l>
                        <l>For thy owne Fates bestow this stile on thee,</l>
                        <l>King both to men and children, yet in them</l>
                        <l>Thou was more fierce to children then to men:</l>
                        <l>Which when the fates perceiu'd, they thoght t'extend</l>
                        <l>Thy course continued il with swifter end.</l>
                        <l>Spurne not against the fates, imperious foole,</l>
                        <l>For as thou lost thy crown, thouse leaue thy scoole</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>Epitaphs</hi> of this nature, a more then morall instruction or institution is to be required: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing onely the intellectuall part without any prophane or heathenish inuention, being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent to the vulgar reach or apprehension of humane vnderstanding: many diuine and holy es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cripts of the ancient Fathers may be comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded heerein: being such as treated aswell of the life and discipline of the dead, as especiall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of imitation; or cautions of detestation to the liuing. Here Ambition pourtraied in her co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, occasions her owne end by her owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded desires. There Couetousnesse (with the
<pb facs="tcp:178199:29"/> misers Motto) is exemplified, and how many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils are continually attending her, according to the definitiue censure of <hi>Flaccus, Semper a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arus eget.</hi> Heere Sacriledge instanced in our ancient <hi>Albane Brennus;</hi> on whom we reade, that after his many conquests and victorious attempts in <hi>Gaule,</hi> and the sacking of Rome, with many rich booties and spoiles obtained in those warres; at last attempted the beautifull and rich Temple of <hi>Delphos</hi> consecrate to <hi>Apollo,</hi> being excited and instigated by <hi>Euridanus</hi> and <hi>Thessalonus</hi> to aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture so difficult a Prouince, onely in hope of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining inestimable treasures, reserued (say they) for such as would boldly attempt, and without feare of the gods, or prophanation of Religion, durst attempt the ransacking and rifling of such sacred treasures. But behold, the purposes of the wicked were confounded (and euer may Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge haue the like successe) for suddenly <hi>Brennus</hi> with all his populous Armie, were discomfited, their execrable deuices frustrated, and themselues (all or most) subiected to miserable ends: the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars whereof are more fully and amply dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on by the Romane Historian <hi>Trog. Pompeius.</hi> Their <hi>Epitaph</hi> we finde thus, (being extracted out of ancient Annals) concording well with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of their crime, and miserie of their end:
<q>
                        <l>Haec via Sacrilegis, haec regia porta sepultis,</l>
                        <l>A Delphi laribus limen adire Ditis.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:29"/>
                  <p>In English thus,
<q>
                        <l>This way Church-robbers go, who seek to fall</l>
                        <l>From great <hi>Apolloes</hi> shrine to <hi>Plutoes</hi> Hall.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>These kind of <hi>Epitaphs</hi> may include or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all such, as for any excellent part or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement domestike or publique, haue beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy memory: or such, as for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of place haue beene no lesse markeable, then singular in discharge of their authoritie: for acts of puissance &amp; renowme that <hi>Epitaph</hi> engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen on the Tombe of <hi>Willinam Marshall</hi> Earle of Pembroke, in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the third:
<q>
                        <l>Sum quem Saturnum sibi sensit Hybernia; Solem</l>
                        <l>Anglia, Mercurum Normannia, Gallia Martem.</l>
                     </q> And that <hi>Epitaph</hi> writ vpon <hi>Theobald Blois</hi> Earle of Champaine (too diuine for any mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Non hominem possum, non andeo dicere numen.</hi> And that of one <hi>Glare</hi> expressing (in one man) an Epitome of all vertues:
<q>
                        <l>Hic pudor Hippoliti, Paridis gena, sensus <hi>Vlyssis,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Aeneae pietas, <hi>Hectoris</hi> ira iacet.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>That memorable one also vpon the Sepulcher of <hi>Maud</hi> mother to <hi>Henrie</hi> the second: descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the excellencie of her descent by her Father, the greatnesse of her selfe by her match, and her renowmed issue which (of all other) made her
<pb facs="tcp:178199:30"/> most admired, and after death the especiallest motiue of her eternall memorie.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Ortu magna, Viro maior, sed maxima partu,</l>
                     <l>Hîc iacet <hi>Henrici</hi> filia, sponsa, parens.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Ancient times haue esteemed these <hi>Epitaphs</hi> suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in themselues to perpetuate their names, being records euer true: for as the Orator saith, <hi>Quis tam infaelici genio, leuique ingenio qui mortuis assentari cupit?</hi> and as the Poet saith,<note n="a" place="margin">Lucan.</note>
                     <hi>Quis Busta timebit? Herostratus</hi> was charactred aswell for his infamie, as <hi>Themisto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> for his renowme and chiualrie. Euen <hi>Metel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> modestie, <hi>Lentulus</hi> leuitie, <hi>Publicolas</hi> pietie, <hi>Cethegus</hi> crueltie, <hi>Appius</hi> affabilitie, and <hi>Ciceroes</hi> constancie had their true lineatures: euery one mouldned and moulded after their deserts: for these, as examples, be of more power and efficacie to the practise and prosecution of vertue, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny instructiō or document whatsoeuer; draw men more attentiuely to their imitation, whose ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues they see merit admiration, as I haue in part before touched. It is the Historians obseruation, that such as had worthy and vertuous Parents, were wont to repaire vnto their Tombs <hi>(Quasi ad propria vitae documenta)</hi> and by their memory to be excited to the like meanes of atchieuing glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and renowme, that their ends might answere such exemplarie parents. Though it was <hi>Lycas</hi> conclusion in the Tragedie, to attribute all merit
<pb facs="tcp:178199:30"/> to ones proper action, and not to the honour of their Auncestor. True it is indeed, that our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors glory cannot properly be entitled ours, their actions being onely as monuments of their fame, presidents for vs to follow, and indeed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimers of our bastardy, if we chance to dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate from such rare and exquisite mirrors. Yet was <hi>Sextus Pompeius</hi> honoured for his Fathers worth: and such as descended from vertuous pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, were onely thought fit to match with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricians.</hi> Those foure<note n="b" place="margin">Aureliae, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, Laeliae, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neliae.</note> ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies in Rome, whose vertuous and modest demeanures got them the name of chast matrons, were well portraied by proper <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> and in their memory were these sentences engrauen: <hi>Heere Romes honour lies buried: Heere lies the foundation of Auncient families:</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Heere modest <hi>Laelius</hi> from his <hi>Laelia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pompey</hi> the yonger from <hi>Cornelia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>From <hi>Mutia,</hi> came a <hi>Mutius Sceuola,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And good <hi>Aurelius</hi> from <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>By these memorable Impresses, were their suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors ennobled, and to their imitation more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently excited then by any precept or instruction whatsoeuer: the cause may be drawne from that affectation of honour naturally ingraffed in vs from our birth, whereby we vse to be spurred and instigated to the imitating of such as by any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:178199:31"/> demerit either inherent in themselues, or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from others to themselues, haue purchased renowme: whence it is, that the Poet saith: <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mensum calcar gloria habet:</hi> neither hath it beene accounted a little glory, or slender honour for the successors of so noble and famous Auncestors: whose monuments were as Annals of their worth and proclaimers of their glory; which that they might preserue the better, they vsed to solemnize their Funerals with exceeding honours, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their Sepulchers with all state and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, deputing Surueiours (which should look to the erection and preseruation thereof:) calling euer their graues <hi>Accommodatissima vitae specimina,</hi> Without which the memory of their vertues might seeme obscured, their glory darkened, and a great many of those excellent parts wherewith they were endued, buried in silence and obliuion. True it is, that gorgeous Sepulchers little auaile the dead: which moued the Philosopher to say, that they were not so much made for the dead, as for the liuing. The Orator termed them mirrors of humane frailtie, characters of our glory, and vndoubted Arguments of our mortalitie. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examplifying this more fully saith, <hi>They are Glasses wherein we may contemplate our selues and others, motiues of imitation wherein we may follow others, and images of affinitie being of the like nature and substance with others.</hi> No better or more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Resemblance can be made twixt man and his
<pb facs="tcp:178199:31"/> creation, the image of his life, and necessitie of his dissolution; the state of his birth, and occasion of his death; the forme of his beginning, and fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his end, then twixt a dead-mans Sepulcher, and the Worlds Theatre. Heere many Actors (some whereof like your <hi>Pantomimes</hi> in Rome, are generally approued in all parts) play on this terrestriall stage of humane frailtie. Some abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Machiauels (irreligious politicians) shrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vicious purposes vnder vertuous pretences: other simple-honest soules, who (like your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure Actor) stands either not at all obserued, or else so generally derided, as he wisheth rather to be a doore-keeper in the mansions of Heauen, then a disgraced Actor on this stage of Earth. There your light Curtizan (who like another<note n="c" place="margin">Salust.</note>
                     <hi>Semphronia, tanta est libidine accensa vt viros saepius petet, quâm petetur,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutes her body to ruinate her soule, exposing her selfe to all, that she might become hatefull to all: to be briefe, in the surueigh of all states and conditions (for euery particular vice incurres a peculiar shame) we may bring the Miser to his graue, who while he liued, was subiect to his vice: The Curtizan from her brothell of vanitie, to her fellow-pupils hearse, there to contemplate her owne frailty. The Ambitious skie-soaring thoughts, to Ambicions fall, reducing his aspy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring spirit, to a more retired centure, the period of a great mans hopes; which moued <hi>Praxatiles</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:32"/>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Sceptrum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, in centrum vergit.</note> to limne an ambitious man rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching at a Scepter, and rowling be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Centre. Not a vice either occurrent to state publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, obnoxious to themselues or others, but was expressed in that flourishing time, when Rome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored of her owne greatnesse; so as <hi>Catilines</hi> Tombe became a caution for aspirers; <hi>Seianus</hi> a president for Flatterers; <hi>Vitellius</hi> an example for Rioters; <hi>Iulian</hi> for apostates and prophaners; <hi>Marke Antonie</hi> for adulterate meetings; <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula</hi> for tyrannike designements. <hi>Quod meruere tenent post funera:</hi> their liues being set out in liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly colours, either in expression of their worth, or the description of their illimited gouernment. Many we reade (and those worthy memorie) who throgh want of these inscriptions had their liuing names shut vp in eternall silence, as the<note n="e" place="margin">Plutarch. in vit.</note> mothers of <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias,</hi> of <hi>Lamachus,</hi> of <hi>Phormion,</hi> of <hi>Thrasibulus,</hi> and of <hi>Theramenes</hi> which excelled in modestie, and well deserued to be mothers of such rare Captaines, eloquent Orators, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete States-men as they were. We reade in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> how <hi>Alcibiades</hi> assisted by <hi>Nicias,</hi> was to take his expedition into Sicilie, the very same day of the celebration of the feast <hi>Adonia,</hi> on which the custome was, that women should set vp in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers parts of the Citie, in the midst of the streetes, Images like to dead coarses, which they caried to
<pb facs="tcp:178199:32"/> buriall in remembrance of the lamentations and disconsolate passions which <hi>Venus</hi> expressed for the death of her <hi>Adonis:</hi> where in this solemnitie, their imaginarie hearses were set ful of Impresses, that their Funerall might be with more state and magnificence celebrated. But hauing discoursed before of the antiquitie of <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> with their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speciall vses appropriate, as well to ancient as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing times, I will descend to the third<note n="f" place="margin">Definition of the third Branch.</note> branch, which in my first diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion I propounded my selfe; to wit, <hi>Epitaphs</hi> Prophane, being such as haue beene vsed to anatomise vice satyrically, (with an Inuection against the manners of the dead: which seemes different to the Philosophers instruction, aduising vs rather to treade lightly on the graues of the dead, and to passe ouer their obliquities with a modest pace, a conniuing eye, and a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iudgement; that our pace might not presse them, our eye pierce them, nor our iudgement poyze them, but in the skale of amitie, with the eye of pittie, and the feete of lenitie. But now to our discourse, and that briefely, whereby the shortnesse of our Volume may concord with our intention.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epitaphs</hi> of this sort we haue too frequent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forged out of the braine of vnseasoned Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rists, that without distinction bend their wits to aspers<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> imputation vpon the deserued memorie of the dead: men of basest nature, defaming such
<pb facs="tcp:178199:33"/> whose silence giues them freer scope and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of detraction: impious violaters of burials, commentors of imaginarie vices, wrongers of the dead, enuious libellers, who write either incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed through spleene, or hired for price: drawne on by others, or voluntarily moued by their own depraued and distempered inclinations; of which kinde we may reade euery Nation (euen in their flourishingst and successiuest times) to haue had their part: Athens her <hi>Eupolis,</hi> Sparta her <hi>Alcae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">In Cyrus time.</note> Persia her <hi>Aristeas,</hi> Rome her <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilus.</hi> These trode not with easie pace on the graues of the dead, but mixing their inke with more gall then discretion, instiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more by splene then charitable affection, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacked the Sepulchers of their dead enemies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blazoned their vices dying, which (through a slauish pusillanimitie, they durst not vnrip nor discouer liuing; these remorselesse censurers of Vices, these corrupters and stamers of well meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted liues, these foes to vertue, and foments of vice, were well set out by the Tragike Poet: who brought in the Ghost of the wronged person, pursuing the detractour and menacing him with eternall reproach for his labour. Yet this digres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion may seeme not so much impertinent as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly repugnant to my first definition of <hi>Epitaphs</hi> and <hi>Epicedes,</hi> the natures of both which I haue in part described: where I defined <hi>Epitaphs</hi> to be nothing else then Testimonials of the Vertues or
<pb facs="tcp:178199:33"/> Vices of the dead: how they were affected, or what especiall occurrents happened them in their life; it is true, but these Descriptions are to bee shadowed and suited with modest allusions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually disposed Allegories as their vices, though in part discouered, yet that discouery so intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled as may minister matter of obseruation to the iudicious, and leaue the ignorant in a continuall suspence. And because we produced no authority before (touching the difference twixt an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph</hi> and <hi>Epicede</hi>) wee will vse <hi>Seruius</hi> opinion heerein: the difference is betweene an <hi>Epicede</hi> and <hi>Epitaph,</hi> as <hi>Seruius</hi> teacheth, that the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede</hi> is before the corps be interred, an <hi>Epitaph</hi> or inscription vpon the Tombe: the etymologie of the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> —<hi>curare inferias,</hi> or <hi>funeris offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia peragere. Scaliger</hi> in his authoritie of Poets, confirmes the deriuation as proper and genuine to the nature of funerall celebrities. This distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction may (serue as a threed to guide the illiterate <hi>Poetaster</hi> (who perhaps otherwise would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found these two words) out of the labyrinth of error, in which more writers now adaies wander, then euer in any time before. So that it may seem the paradox of <hi>Erasmus</hi> in the praise of folly, and that booke which <hi>Agrippa</hi> writ <hi>De vanitate sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiarum,</hi> are subiects onely in request; where e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>Mauius</hi> will write (and ofttimes be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) aswell as <hi>Maro. Aiax</hi> in <hi>Euripides</hi> said: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, To know nothing is the
<pb facs="tcp:178199:34"/> sweetest life Which sweetnes this age hath attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, where it may be truely auerred, that <hi>Neuer Age had more writers, and fewer Authors:</hi> those onely being admitted of as<note n="h" place="margin">Doctorum dicta indoctos doctiores reddunt.</note> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, whose workes merit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation and authoritie in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues: experience being redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ignorance, and a desire of knowledge to a fruitlesse desire of writing: <hi>Littora bobus arant, &amp; arena semina mandant.</hi> But I omit them: these prophane <hi>Epitaphs</hi> sinisterly aiming at the detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of such who rest in peace, as they are vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be condemned, so their Authors as presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of such obliquities should be seuerely cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured, whereby an example of punishment in one might minister cause of reformation in all: yet because sin should in some sort be vnmasked, lest vice sue out a priuiledge, and purchase her selfe a monopoly amongst our world-statists (whose best of traffique is to be the Diuels factors, whose emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentst degree is to be Hels purueiors, and whose onely office in request is to be Mammons colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors) I haue instanced diuers <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented, others translated &amp; traduced from others, which with a tollerable sharpnesse, and a well tempered bitternesse alluding to the persons on whose Tombes they were engrauen, modestly discouer vice in her natiuest colors. As, first in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of Auarice, a vice most incident to Age, and therefore most inherent to man. <hi>Hermon</hi> drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:178199:34"/> he had disbursed money, died for woe, on which dreaming Miser we reade this written:
<q>
                        <l>Vnder heere old <hi>Hermon</hi> lies,</l>
                        <l>Who sleeping liu'd, and dreaming dies.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that of <hi>Phedon</hi> who wept not for that he should die, but that the charge of his buriall should come to foure shillings.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Heere <hi>Phedon</hi> lies, who weeps and cries,</l>
                     <l>not that his life he lost,</l>
                     <l>But that the charge of his Buriall</l>
                     <l>should full foure shillings cost.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And that of <hi>Hermocrates,</hi> who would not be at charge for a purgation: and dying made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe sole Executour:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hermocrates</hi> that catiffe wretch,</l>
                        <l>who liuing had no power</l>
                        <l>To vse his owne, did make himselfe</l>
                        <l>his sole executour.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that of <hi>None,</hi> whose Name and nature had relation one to another, being only to himselfe without respect of publike good, or compassion to others want:
<q>
                        <l>Heere lieth<note n="i" place="margin">
                              <l>Hic situs est Nullus, quia Nullo Nullior esto,</l>
                              <l>Et quia Nullus erat, de Nullo Nil tibi Christe.</l>
                           </note>
                           <hi>None</hi> by name, by nature one,</l>
                        <l>Yet was he one by Name, by nature None.</l>
                        <l>Something of Nothing oft the poore did craue,</l>
                        <l>Yet could the poore of Nothing, nothing haue.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:35"/>
                  <p>And that of one<note n="k" place="margin">Hic situs est si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiens atque Ebrius Eldertonus; quid dico hic situs est, hic potius sitis est?</note>
                     <hi>Elderton,</hi> (an inscription too bitter) yet to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>authorize that sin, (which like that powerfull ointment whereof <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leius</hi> relates, amongst the Thessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians, transforming and meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphosing men into bruite beasts) to wit drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennesse, whereof he was taxed, nothing can be too vehement or violent:
<q>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Camban Romain.</note>Heere drunken <hi>Elderton</hi> in earth lies thrust,</l>
                        <l>Lies thrust (say I) or rather heere lies thirst.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will end this last part of my diuision (fearing much I haue insisted too long vpon the preamble, and incurring the Mindian censure of making my gate so spacious, and the maine building so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted:) I will end (I say) with that vniuersall doome and home (with which mortalitie must of necessitie end) to wit, <hi>Dust:</hi> of which name we reade one to haue beene, and ceasing to be, had this inscription:
<q>
                        <l>Heere <hi>Dust</hi> lies dead, who that he might be iust</l>
                        <l>In Name and Nature, while he liu'd lou'd dust,</l>
                        <l>And being dust by Nature and by Name,</l>
                        <l>Thought to returne to dust from whence he came.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="poems">
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:35"/>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ A Description of Death.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>DEath is a raw bon'd shrimp, nor low nor hie,</l>
                        <l>Yet haz he power to make the highest low,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Summon-maister</hi> of mortalitie,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Poore mans wished friend,</hi> the <hi>Rich-mans</hi> foe,</l>
                        <l>The last <hi>Remaines</hi> of <hi>Times Anatomie,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A Thiefe</hi> in pace, in pace more sure then slow;</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Sleepe,</hi> a <hi>Dreame,</hi> whence we are said to haue</l>
                        <l>In sleepe a <hi>Death,</hi> and in our <hi>Bed</hi> a graue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>One who, how ere we seeme to haue the power</l>
                        <l>To leaue our states, wherein we oft-times erre,</l>
                        <l>To such an one as sole executour;</l>
                        <l>Spite of our nose playes Executioner;</l>
                        <l>And as the <hi>Leane Kine</hi> did the <hi>Fat</hi> deuoure,</l>
                        <l>So does this meagre <hi>Slaue</hi> the mightier,</l>
                        <l>Nor can we if we should be choaked for't,</l>
                        <l>Remoue <hi>Deaths Action</hi> to another Court.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Arts</hi> though <hi>He</hi> know, yet he professeth none,</l>
                        <l>For little haz <hi>He,</hi> and as little needes,</l>
                        <l>Yet haz he <hi>Trickes</hi> to catch the oldest one,</l>
                        <l>That on this earthie <hi>Globe</hi> or centre treades,</l>
                        <l>Nor will <hi>He</hi> leaue him till his Breath be gone,</l>
                        <l>Cheering the wormes that on his Body feedes:</l>
                        <l>Thus fearelesse <hi>He,</hi> as he haz euer beene,</l>
                        <l>Makes his stroke to be felt, not to be seene.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:36"/>
                        <l>His Signe's in <hi>Sagittary,</hi> and the But</l>
                        <l>He shootes at is mans heart, <hi>He</hi> euer fits</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The shafts he shootes</hi> to th'Quiuer they are put;</l>
                        <l>Won is <hi>He</hi> not to be by threats, intreats,</l>
                        <l>Price, power or prayer: at whats'ere <hi>He</hi> shoote</l>
                        <l>Or aimes to hit, <hi>He</hi> neuer failes but hits;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Darted, He runnes as swift as euer ran,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shot-herring made, iust like an Irish-man.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor differ they in habite; though <hi>He</hi> weares</l>
                        <l>No <hi>Mantle, flanning trowses,</hi> being knowne</l>
                        <l>By his <hi>Moath-eaten rayment, He</hi> appeares</l>
                        <l>Right Irish, <hi>Doublet, Breeches,</hi> hose of one;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> haz no shift, yet <hi>He</hi> no <hi>vermin</hi> feares,</l>
                        <l>(For <hi>vermin, Death,</hi> nor th' Irish harbour none)</l>
                        <l>Yea in their kinde of fight compar'd <hi>They</hi> are,</l>
                        <l>For <hi>They</hi> inuade vs both at vnaware.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Death</hi> is wormes-Caterer, who when <hi>He</hi> comes</l>
                        <l>Will haue prouision though the Market starue,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> will be seru'd before the mighty ones,</l>
                        <l>And knows before where <hi>He</hi> intends to carue;</l>
                        <l>Its <hi>He</hi> awakes the <hi>Sin-belulled Drones,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And cuts <hi>Them</hi> short as rightly <hi>They</hi> deserue,</l>
                        <l>Its <hi>He</hi> that all things to subiection brings,</l>
                        <l>And plaies at foot-ball with the crowns of kings.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Two empty <hi>Lodges</hi> haz <hi>He</hi> in his head,</l>
                        <l>Which had two <hi>Lights,</hi> but now his <hi>Eies</hi> be gone,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cheekes</hi> had <hi>He</hi> once, but they be hollowed;</l>
                        <l>Beauty <hi>He</hi> had, but now appeares there none:</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:36"/>
                        <l>For all those mouing parts be vanished,</l>
                        <l>Presenting Horrour if but lookt vpon;</l>
                        <l>His colour sable, and his visage grim,</l>
                        <l>With gastly lookes that still attend on <hi>Him.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fleshie He</hi> was, but it is pickt away,</l>
                        <l>Belike, for that <hi>He</hi> haz so much to doe,</l>
                        <l>If cloath'd with <hi>Flesh,</hi> he should be forc'd to stay,</l>
                        <l>And shew (perchance) too much of mercie to</l>
                        <l>To some <hi>Yong wench,</hi> who on the holyday</l>
                        <l>Might force <hi>Him loue, if she could tell him</hi> how;</l>
                        <l>Which to preuent, and better to restraine him,</l>
                        <l>He goes so vgly none should entertaine him.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet entertain'd <hi>He</hi> will; for though <hi>He be</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Contemn'd by th' perfum'd Curtezan, whose form</l>
                        <l>Seemes coy to giue <hi>Him</hi> hospitalitie;</l>
                        <l>Yet when <hi>He</hi> comes <hi>Hee'l</hi> not one houre adiorne,</l>
                        <l>To giue her Summons of mortalitie;</l>
                        <l>Conuerting that same Beautie, did adorne</l>
                        <l>Her Composition to corrupted earth,</l>
                        <l>Whence she deriu'd both Period and Birth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Snaile-like <hi>He</hi> comes on vs with creeping pace,</l>
                        <l>And takes vs napping whē we least think on him,</l>
                        <l>In's hand an <hi>Houre-glasse,</hi> which inferres our race</l>
                        <l>Is neare an end; and though we striue to shun him,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> moues when we moue; and that very place</l>
                        <l>Whereto we flie, and think we haue out-run him,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>There</hi> he appeares, and tells <hi>vs</hi> it's not good</l>
                        <l>To striue 'gainst that which cannot be withstood.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:37"/>
                        <l>If we shed teares, they're bootlesse, for his <hi>eyes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In stead of sight are moulded vp with clay,</l>
                        <l>If we assay to pierce his eares with cries,</l>
                        <l>Vaine is our <hi>Labour,</hi> fruitlesse our assay;</l>
                        <l>For his <hi>Remorcelesse eares</hi> all motions flies,</l>
                        <l>Nor will <hi>He</hi> giue the Prince a longer day:</l>
                        <l>His payment must be present, and his <hi>Doome,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Returne to earth thy Cradle and thy Tombe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor is his Summons onely when we're old,</l>
                        <l>For <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Youth He</hi> equally attends,</l>
                        <l>Nor can we say that we haue firmer hold</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Youth</hi> then <hi>Age</hi> or further from our ends,</l>
                        <l>Saue that we are by Natures verdict told,</l>
                        <l>With length of yeares our hope of life extends:</l>
                        <l>Thus <hi>yong</hi> or <hi>old,</hi> if <hi>Death</hi> approach and say,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Earth vnto Earth, He</hi> must perforce obay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A Breath-bereauing Breath, a vading shade,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Euer in motion, so as it appeares</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> comes to tell <hi>vs</hi> whereto we were made,</l>
                        <l>And like a <hi>friend</hi> to rid <hi>vs</hi> of our feares,</l>
                        <l>So as if his approach were rightly weighed,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He</hi> shold be welcom'd more with ioyes thē tears,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ioy</hi> to dissolue to earth from whence we came,</l>
                        <l>That after <hi>Death, Ioy</hi> might receiue the <hi>same.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Naked his scalpe, thrill-open is his Nose,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His Mouth from eare to eare, his earthie Breath</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Corrupt and noysome.</hi> Which makes me suppose</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Some mouldie cell's the Mannor-house of Death:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:37"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His shapelesse legges bend backeward when he goes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His rake-leane body shrinking vnderneath,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Feeble he seemes, rest both of heart and power,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet dare he <hi>beard</hi> the mightiest <hi>Emperour.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>None <hi>He</hi> consorts with saue wormes and men</l>
                        <l>Prepar'd for worms-meat, though he make resort</l>
                        <l>To Country, City, Village now and then,</l>
                        <l>Yea where hee's seldome welcome, to the <hi>Court,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>There will <hi>He</hi> enter, and will summon them;</l>
                        <l>And goe <hi>they</hi> must, though <hi>they</hi> be sorie for't:</l>
                        <l>Thus, <hi>Country, Citie, Village, Court and all,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Must their appearāce make when <hi>Death</hi> doth call.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Chop-falne, Crest-sunke, drie-bon'd Anatomie,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Earth-turn'd, mole-ei'd, flesh-hook</hi> that puls vs hēce</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Night-crow, Fates-doome,</hi> that tells vs we must die,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pilgrim-remouer</hi> that depriues vs sence;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Lifes-date, Soules-gate</hi> that leades from miserie,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mans sharp'st assault</hi> admitting no defence,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Times Exit,</hi> or our <hi>Intrat</hi> to that <hi>Clime,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Where there's no <hi>Time,</hi> nor <hi>Period</hi> of <hi>Time.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor stands he much vpon our dangerous yeare,</l>
                        <l>All are alike to <hi>Him,</hi> yea oft we see,</l>
                        <l>When we are most secure, then <hi>Hee's</hi> most neare,</l>
                        <l>Where th' <hi>yeare clymactericke</hi> is his <hi>Iubile:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For as <hi>He</hi> can transpose <hi>Him</hi> euery where,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>East, West, North, South,</hi> with all facilitie,</l>
                        <l>So can <hi>He</hi> come, so cunning is his stealth,</l>
                        <l>And take <hi>vs</hi> hence when we are best in health.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:38"/>
                        <l>Since <hi>Death</hi> is thus describ'd, (for this he is,)</l>
                        <l>Be still <hi>prepar'd, lest vnprepar'd He</hi> come,</l>
                        <l>And hale you hence, for spending <hi>Time</hi> amisse</l>
                        <l>(For <hi>Death is Sins Reward, Transgressions Doome</hi>)</l>
                        <l>So when <hi>thou dies</hi> thou shalt be sure of this,</l>
                        <l>To haue <hi>accesse</hi> vnto the <hi>Marriage</hi> roome,</l>
                        <l>And for thy <hi>Tombe,</hi> in steade of <hi>Iuorie,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Marble,</hi> or <hi>Brasse,</hi> shall <hi>Ʋertue couer thee.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:38"/>
                     <head>Epitaphs vpon sudden and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature deaths: occasioned vpon some occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> lately and vnhappily arising.</head>
                     <l>WHo walkes this way? what Charitie, ist thou?</l>
                     <l>I need not feare thy doome: for thou'lt allow</l>
                     <l>This Axiome for vndoubted: Once we must</l>
                     <l>Returne vnto our mother earth: and dust</l>
                     <l>Our first creation, challengeth the same:</l>
                     <l>"Being the <hi>Mould</hi> from whence our bodies came.</l>
                     <l>If Enuie passe this way and iudge amisse,</l>
                     <l>"I rest secure what ere her censure is.</l>
                     <l>Faith is my Anchor, Comfort is my Shield,</l>
                     <l>"How should I doubt then but to win the field!</l>
                     <l>For this is true (as I haue oft times heard)</l>
                     <l>No death is sudden to a minde prepar'd.</l>
                     <l>My Hope being thus erected; Enuie, cease</l>
                     <l>"To wrong his soule that haz assured peace.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Another Epitaph vpon the same subiect.</head>
                     <l>Thou look'st vpon my Tombe, and wagg'st thy head,</l>
                     <l>And with remorcefull teares weep'st ore me dead,</l>
                     <l>As if past hope: thou seem'st to be my frend,</l>
                     <l>In that thou grieu'st at my vntimely end:</l>
                     <l>Vntimely dost thou call it? True: report</l>
                     <l>Brutes my Repentance was but very short,</l>
                     <l>Because cut off: I graunt it: for the space</l>
                     <l>It was but short, yet was the course of grace</l>
                     <l>Abundant, which confirmes my Pilgrims wish,</l>
                     <l>"Where man's prepar'd, there no death sudden is.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:39"/>
                     <head>An Epitaph of the same.</head>
                     <l>Hopelesse thou weep'st, and com'st vnto my Tombe,</l>
                     <l>Descanting on my death, with, oh too soone</l>
                     <l>Dide this poore wretch: I pray thee ceasse to weepe,</l>
                     <l>"I am not dead, but onely falne asleepe:</l>
                     <l>A blessed sleepe, secure from Enuies sting,</l>
                     <l>"Flying from earth to heauen with ayrie wing:</l>
                     <l>Should'st thou then doubt my end? O do not doubt,</l>
                     <l>"My virgin-lampe is in, 't shall nere goe out.</l>
                     <l>Thou saist I dide too soone: thou saist amisse,</l>
                     <l>"Can any die too soone to liue in Blisse?</l>
                     <l>Wipe then thy Teares, I know thou wish me well,</l>
                     <l>Heauen is my mansion, Earth I tooke for hell:</l>
                     <l>And that was cause I went so soone from thence,</l>
                     <l>To plant in Heauen my eternall residence:</l>
                     <l>For men (how short their end) are neuer tride,</l>
                     <l>"But how they learn'd to die before they dide.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a vertuous young Lady dying in child-birth.</head>
                     <l>Borne at the first to bring another forth,</l>
                     <l>"She leaues the world, to leaue the world her birth:</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Phoenix</hi>-like as she was borne to breed,</l>
                     <l>"Dying herselfe renews it in her seed.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:39"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Souldier, for resolutiō worthily affected and aduanced by his Country, yet interred and by (vnworthy Fate) obscurely.</head>
                     <l>Dead? Yes: Alas, is this the Souldiers tombe,</l>
                     <l>A silly monument to them shall come</l>
                     <l>To see it. True; what tho the body lie</l>
                     <l>Interred low in her obscuritie?</l>
                     <l>Thy vertue (honour'd Souldier) shall remaine</l>
                     <l>Aboue the Boundiers of triumphing <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>France,</hi> or the Belgicke rampires: what Death may</l>
                     <l>Sh' haz done already, turnd thy corpse to clay:</l>
                     <l>But death (of Fames possession) may despaire,</l>
                     <l>For she erects her Tombe within the Ayre,</l>
                     <l>That whosoeuer this way chance to moue,</l>
                     <l>"Shall see his corpse heere, but his fame aboue.</l>
                     <l>Triumphant Souldiers, glorious by thy birth,</l>
                     <l>Reign'st now in heauen, because thou wer'st in earth:</l>
                     <l>Then such <hi>Professants</hi> euer blessed are,</l>
                     <l>That raise their <hi>Peace</hi> by managements of warre.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vpon a Drunkard buried in a ruinous fort in <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> was this Inscription engrauen, which by the ancientnesse of Time was well neare defaced.</head>
                     <l>In <hi>Dunkerke</hi> heere a Drunkard lies with mickle care ysought,</l>
                     <l>"Drinke was the boone the lorden crau'd for rest he cared nought.</l>
                     <l>Long may he wun in this large Tombe, and neuer henceforth sinke</l>
                     <l>"To earth again: that while he liu'd caimd earth for wāt of drink:</l>
                     <l>Heauen rest his soule, and others all, whosere the Lord will saue,</l>
                     <l>"And grant Dunkerk (if't be thy wil) may nere such drūkards haue.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epigram">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:40"/>
                     <head>¶ An Epigram vpon <hi>Alphonso</hi> Prince of <hi>Naples,</hi> and vpon his Crest, whereon was engrauen a Pellican with this Impressa; <hi>Alios seruans meipsum perdo.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>The Crest I weare expresseth what I am,</l>
                     <l>"A soft and tender-hearted Pellican,</l>
                     <l>Who to recall life to her dying broode,</l>
                     <l>Suckes from her owne heart life-renewing blood:</l>
                     <l>Being the same, if I appeale to time,</l>
                     <l>"Shee's not more deare to hers, then I to mine.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ An Epitaph vpon one who died confined.</head>
                     <l>Report tells me that thou didst die confinde;</l>
                     <l>Confinde! its true: in body, not in minde.</l>
                     <l>Confinde the body was, where it had birth,</l>
                     <l>But minde without confinement leaueth earth,</l>
                     <l>To dwell in those refined Groues aboue,</l>
                     <l>A Groue refin'd which yeelds eternall loue</l>
                     <l>To the possessor; let thy minde appeare</l>
                     <l>Free, though thy body was confined heere.</l>
                     <l>This shall remaine engrauen vpon thy Tombe,</l>
                     <l>To memorise thy fame in time to come.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Iustice worthily deseruing of his Countrey.</head>
                     <l>The misse of thee, since thy decease, is knowne,</l>
                     <l>"For whoso comes to Iustice, or her throne,</l>
                     <l>Shall see her silent (and as one thats domb:)</l>
                     <l>"Good reason why, with thee she lost her tongue.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:40"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Iustice of lesse demerite.</head>
                     <l>Who comes this way? Let him looke downe and reade,</l>
                     <l>"Here lies one, spake lesse liuing, then being dead:</l>
                     <l>For heere in Rime Fame speakes of him in time,</l>
                     <l>"Who whilst he liu'd spake Reason nor good Rime,</l>
                     <l>This yet his comfort is, when time is spent,</l>
                     <l>God will haue mercie on the innocent.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a bragging Souldier.</head>
                     <l>Heere lies a bragging Souldier that could lie</l>
                     <l>With pompe and state, in face of maiestie;</l>
                     <l>Yet he that lied' gainst heauen, in earth now lies,</l>
                     <l>An open mirrour to all mortall eies:</l>
                     <l>"For though he lied, yet could he not denie</l>
                     <l>With all his lies, but man is prest to die.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vpon <hi>Peter</hi> see me</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peter see me,</hi> thou canst not, for thy eies</l>
                     <l>"Lie there interred, where thy body lies:</l>
                     <l>How canst thou see me then? as <hi>Peters</hi> doe;</l>
                     <l>"Not by my worth, but by my outward shew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>For Gallant-like by perfumes I transpose</l>
                     <l>My knowledge from thy eies vnto thy nose.</l>
                     <l>That though th'art dead, yet thou may well perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e,</l>
                     <l>"A <hi>Perfum'd gallant walk's vpon thy graue.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:41"/>
                     <head>¶Vpon a Captaine which in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries was hanged, and afterwards taken vp againe.</head>
                     <l>A Captaine hangd, and taken from his Graue,</l>
                     <l>For what? a pardon came, and did him saue.</l>
                     <l>Saue. what did it saue? his body: Yes.</l>
                     <l>"From putrefaction? no, but from that peace</l>
                     <l>All buried corps enioy: It was not done</l>
                     <l>"With Iustice: Yes, she is a Saint diuine,</l>
                     <l>And raisd him vp, because dead'fore his time.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Turner or Thrower that died in his throwing.</head>
                     <l>Poore Thrower, art thou dead? Now do I feele</l>
                     <l>"Euen by thy <hi>End,</hi> that Fortune haz a wheele,</l>
                     <l>That spinnes and weaues, turnes and returnes againe;</l>
                     <l>And in mens death esteemes the chiefest gaine:</l>
                     <l>For this by thee may very well be knowne,</l>
                     <l>That made their owne wheele ruinate thy owne.</l>
                     <l>Thou wast a Thrower, Fate a Thrower too;</l>
                     <l>After this cast thou'lt neere make such a throw:</l>
                     <l>Rest then in peace, it's Fate tript vp thy heele,</l>
                     <l>And bids thee yeeld vnto her Turning wheele.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:41"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Span.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Rightly compared is the life of man,</l>
                     <l>"For shortnesse of continuance, to a span,</l>
                     <l>It is mans <hi>met-wand;</hi> euery one must haue</l>
                     <l>"This span to end his life, and mete his graue.</l>
                     <l>Then who dare say that he does liue secure,</l>
                     <l>"Possessing that which cannot long endure.</l>
                     <l>This is expressed by this man lies heere,</l>
                     <l>"Whose name and nature in one span appeare.</l>
                     <l>So lest the name should do the nature wrong,</l>
                     <l>"Being short by nature, name would not be long.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Flower</hi> a hopefull yong Student.</head>
                     <l>Mans life's a flower: how should it then but fade,</l>
                     <l>"Since at the first for dying it was made?</l>
                     <l>Yet if this Flower had beene exempted, then</l>
                     <l>We might haue thought this Flower not for men</l>
                     <l>To crop: no more it was: and therefore giuen</l>
                     <l>"As one aboue desert of earth to Heauen.</l>
                     <l>Once thou was planted in the Cambrian Groue,</l>
                     <l>Where thou was watred with the Students loue.</l>
                     <l>But now from thence I see thy glory rise,</l>
                     <l>"From Cambrian <hi>Brakes, to Brookes in paradise.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:42"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Reuerend and honourable Iudge of this land, was this Epitaph inscribed.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Who so would Honours frailetie pictur'd haue,</l>
                        <l>Let him behold that picture in this graue:</l>
                        <l>Where frailetie ne're was with more honours clad,</l>
                        <l>Nor more deseru'd those honours which he had:</l>
                        <l>Had? lasse that we should say, wee had thee; haue</l>
                        <l>Would be a <hi>Tence,</hi> the state would rather craue.</l>
                        <l>Small difference twixt the accents, <hi>Haue</hi> and <hi>Had,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet th' one did cheare vs, th' other makes vs sad.</l>
                        <l>But whence these teares? whence be they? to expresse</l>
                        <l>His worth, our want, his peace, our pensiuenesse:</l>
                        <l>For to discribe him in each liniment,</l>
                        <l>He gaue his tongue vnto the Parlament:</l>
                        <l>His hands to sacred writ, his eare to heare</l>
                        <l>Iudgement pronounc'd, his eye to see more cleare</l>
                        <l>In the surueigh of Iustice, and his feete</l>
                        <l>To walke in paths, for Christian soules most meete.</l>
                        <l>Thus his impartiall tongue, hand, eare, foote, eye,</l>
                        <l>Show'd him a mirror in mortalitie.</l>
                        <l>Yet in his age a Reuerence appeares,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Many are yong in houres, are olde in yeares;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But he was old in both; full seuentie sixe,</l>
                        <l>Surpassing <hi>Dauids</hi> first Arithmeticke:</l>
                        <l>Fift<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> one yeares he with his Lady liu'd,</l>
                        <l>That in himselfe his <hi>race,</hi> might be reuiu'd:</l>
                        <l>For what was by the vertuous <hi>Father</hi> done,</l>
                        <l>Seemes (by resemblance) shadowed in the <hi>Sonne.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:42"/>
                        <l>Sergeant vnto the <hi>Queene,</hi> Iudge o'th kings Bench</l>
                        <l>For twelue yeares space, wherein his eminence</l>
                        <l>Did not transport his passions: <hi>For his thought</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Fixt on his end, esteem'd all honour nought.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus liu'd he, thus he di'de; liu'd long, di'de wel,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Heere Iudge on Earth, now Iudge in Israel.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Terras Astraea reliquit.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Distiction funebre in obit: princip. ob exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miam &amp; corporis &amp; mentis temperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em: qua licet, nos reliquit, altiora petit.</head>
                     <l>Qui formam mirantur, ament Ʋestigia mentis,</l>
                     <l>Illi forma perit, nescit at illa mori.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ An Epitaph vpon the Sonne buried in his Fathers graue.</head>
                     <l>Stand, goe no further: looke but downe and reade,</l>
                     <l>Youth fed that body, on which wormes doe feede.</l>
                     <l>Looke lower downe, and thou portrai'd shalt haue</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Sonne,</hi> both buried in one graue.</l>
                     <l>And what does couer them? poore mother Earth,</l>
                     <l>Which gaue to Sonne and Father both their birth:</l>
                     <l>Thus one to three reduc'd, and three to one,</l>
                     <l>Sonne, Mother, Father; Father, Mother, Sonne.</l>
                     <l>Make then this vse on't wheresoe're thou come.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Earth was thy cradle, Earth must be thy tombe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:43"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon<note n="*" place="margin">Jn hunc fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me modum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponitur à Mart. Epigramma.</note> one who louing ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, died ere hee possest it.</head>
                     <l>Thus fadeth honour and returnes to nought,</l>
                     <l>Which is not got by merit, but is bought:</l>
                     <l>For it affoords th' aspiring minde small good,</l>
                     <l>When wreaths of honour are not drawne from blood,</l>
                     <l>Nor from desert: for honour cannot bide,</l>
                     <l>"Being supported by the stayes of pride.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon Master <hi>Laurence Death,</hi> an Epicede ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate to his Name.</head>
                     <l>Why should one feare to grapple with his Name,</l>
                     <l>"Death thou wast liuing, and art now the same;</l>
                     <l>No, I may say farre more: renewing breath</l>
                     <l>"Tels me th' art liuing; for thou hast kil'd Death.</l>
                     <l>Liue then victorious Saint: still may thou be</l>
                     <l>Though dead by Name, yet fresh in memory.</l>
                     <l>That who so passeth, or shall chance to come</l>
                     <l>This way, may say: <hi>Here lies Deaths liuing Tomb.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Merie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Merie</hi> why liest thou like <hi>Heraclitus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That vs'd to laugh like blith <hi>Democritus?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou seemes in discontent: pray thee tell why</l>
                     <l>"Thou liest so sad? Thou art learning how to die.</l>
                     <l>Learning to die? why th'art already dead:</l>
                     <l>Ist possible that <hi>Peter Meries</hi> head</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:43"/>
                     <l>That was so full of wit, so stuft with sage,</l>
                     <l>"As he appear'd the mirror of this age?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peter</hi> that knew much, and could speake much more</l>
                     <l>Then ere he knew, should now fall to deaths store.</l>
                     <l>Alas poore <hi>Merie,</hi> wormes begin to feast,</l>
                     <l>Ʋpon that skonce, <hi>fed Gallants</hi> with fresh ieasts,</l>
                     <l>Those saucer eyes plast in that witty skonse,</l>
                     <l>Which vs'd to looke some twenty waies at once,</l>
                     <l>For if they had matches beene, some might enquire,</l>
                     <l>Whether they set thy sparkeling-nose a fire:</l>
                     <l>Those hollow <hi>eyes</hi> (I say) or lamps of thine,</l>
                     <l>"Are now like <hi>Hogs-heads emptied of their wine:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For hollow Hogs-heads giue an empty sound,</l>
                     <l>"And so does <hi>Merie</hi> being laide in <hi>ground.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Hogge.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hog</hi> by name and by condition,</l>
                     <l>"Heere lies <hi>Hog</hi> that blunt Physition:</l>
                     <l>Christian nor good moralist,</l>
                     <l>But liu'd and dide an Atheist.</l>
                     <l>Yet (after death) giue <hi>Hog</hi> his dew,</l>
                     <l>He was a foe vnto the Iew.</l>
                     <l>And that he might expresse the same▪</l>
                     <l>"He gloried euer in his name.</l>
                     <l>He bad me write vpon him dead,</l>
                     <l>"<hi>Heere lies Iohn Hog, or Iohn Hogs-head.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:44"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a vaine-glorious Student that would needes be called <hi>Aristarchus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Fate last night hath beene i'th warke house</l>
                     <l>Of our renowmed <hi>Aristarchus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where fate no sooner entred in</l>
                     <l>Then shee a starke-Asse made of him.</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Aristarchus</hi> (Authors say)</l>
                     <l>Inuited death, from day to day;</l>
                     <l>But our last <hi>Aristarchus</hi> prai'd,</l>
                     <l>(Seeing Death come) as one dismaied,</l>
                     <l>That he his summons would delay,</l>
                     <l>And come for him another day.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vpon two Twins that died together</head>
                     <l>Heere lie two faithfull Brothers in one tombe,</l>
                     <l>As they did lie together in one wombe;</l>
                     <l>Heere they came hand in hand, and they do craue,</l>
                     <l>That hand in hand they may goe to their <hi>Graue.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>
                        <note place="margin">In Monasterio septentrion: com pertum erat.</note>¶ Vpon an ancient Tombe was this inscription found.</head>
                     <l>Church-men that should be best of al, are (pardie) growne the worst,</l>
                     <l>The Fox I ken (the Prouerb saies) fares best when he is curst:</l>
                     <l>This Abbot heere that lies in ground proues this to be too true,</l>
                     <l>Due would he giue to Priest nor Cleark, yet would he haue his due;</l>
                     <l>But marke his end (who ere thou be) for 'twas a fearefull end,</l>
                     <l>No friend he had (as he did thinke) to whom he might commend</l>
                     <l>His Gold: therefore one day he went to finde out some darke caue,</l>
                     <l>Where be might hoord his treasure vp where he this voice receau'd:</l>
                     <l>The iudgement churlish <hi>Nabal</hi> had, fall presently on thee,</l>
                     <l>Which voice being past, the Abbot droupt and died presently.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:44"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon my Lady <hi>Woodbee.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>What would my Lady be? lasse shee has sought</l>
                     <l>To rise to something, and shee's falne to nought.</l>
                     <l>Poore Lady, that so faire and sweete a face</l>
                     <l>Should haue no other home or dwelling place,</l>
                     <l>Then a poore Sepulcher; lasse its not meete</l>
                     <l>So faire a Lady should shroud in <hi>one sheete:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who whilst shee liu'd, which was but very now,</l>
                     <l>Did vse to lie perfum'd and chaf'd in two.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon the same Subiect extracted.</head>
                     <l>Looke throgh &amp; throgh, see Ladies with false formes,</l>
                     <l>You deceiue men, but cannot deceiue wormes.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon an Adulterer extracted.</head>
                     <l>Nay heauen is iust, scornes are the hire of scornes,</l>
                     <l>I nere knew yet <hi>Adulterer</hi> without hornes.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Sexton an Epitaph.</head>
                     <l>Rest thee well Sexton, since thou lost thy breath,</l>
                     <l>I see no Man can be exempt from death:</l>
                     <l>For what will Death doe to the simple Slaue,</l>
                     <l>That durst assault <hi>him</hi> made for Death a Graue?</l>
                     <l>In peace sleepe on: of thee we haue no neede,</l>
                     <l>For we haue chosen a Sexton in thy steede:</l>
                     <l>Thy sacring Bell has tinckled all it can,</l>
                     <l>And now the Sexton showes he was a man.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:45"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Kempe</hi> and his morice, with his Epitaph.</head>
                     <l>Welcome from Norwich <hi>Kempe:</hi> all ioy to see</l>
                     <l>Thy safe returne morisceed lustily.</l>
                     <l>But out alasse how soone's thy morice done,</l>
                     <l>When Pipe and Taber all thy friends be gone?</l>
                     <l>And leaue thee now to dance the second part</l>
                     <l>With feeble nature, not with nimble Art:</l>
                     <l>Then all thy triumphs fraught with strains of mirth,</l>
                     <l>"Shall be cag'd vp within a chest of earth:</l>
                     <l>"Shall be? they are, th'ast danc'd thee out of breath,</l>
                     <l>"And now must make thy parting dance with death.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Skelton.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Here lies one <hi>Skelton,</hi> whom death seasing on,</l>
                     <l>"Changeth this <hi>Skelton</hi> vnto<note n="*" place="margin">Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, or an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>omy</note> Sceleton</l>
                     <l>Thogh little chang'd in name, in substāce more,</l>
                     <l>"For now hee's rich that was but poore before.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Of all the stones that rear'd vp Babylon,</l>
                     <l>"There now remaines (of all that pile) but one,</l>
                     <l>Which serues to couer both the corps and fame,</l>
                     <l>Which he had purchas'd onely by his Name.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:45"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a spare Patron.<note place="margin">In patron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> egentem.</note>
                     </head>
                     <l>This Man lies here, to say what name he had,</l>
                     <l>Or to expresse't would make a Poet mad:</l>
                     <l>For once a Poet offred him a labour,</l>
                     <l>Which he would hardly reade, or vouchsafe fauour,</l>
                     <l>To giue the Author one bare smile, or sooth</l>
                     <l>The Poets good meaning: to be briefe, his tooth</l>
                     <l>Was poysoned: for th' occasion of his death,</l>
                     <l>It first proceeded from his stinking breath;</l>
                     <l>Which did corrupt his lungs: this has beene tride</l>
                     <l>To be the cause whereof this <hi>Patron</hi> dide.</l>
                     <l>May he rest yet in peace the Poet prayes,</l>
                     <l>Who though contemn'd, yet crownes his Tombe with bayes.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a cashered Souldier.<note place="margin">In Nether<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land.</note>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Souldier not for his desert</l>
                     <l>Cashered was of late,</l>
                     <l>But for the Captaine by his pay,</l>
                     <l>Ment to encrease his state;</l>
                     <l>For which (in want the Souldier beg'd)</l>
                     <l>But could not be relieu'd:</l>
                     <l>As Charity (God knowes) is cold,</l>
                     <l>Whereat the Souldier grieu'd;</l>
                     <l>And swore since warre would doe no good,</l>
                     <l>He now would change his sang,</l>
                     <l>Either to raise his meanes (by stands)</l>
                     <l>Or Souldier-like to hang.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:46"/>
                     <l>Fate seldome fauours war like men,</l>
                     <l>The case so altered was,</l>
                     <l>As being tane for bidding stand</l>
                     <l>To one that chanc'd to passe,</l>
                     <l>The poore renowme this Souldier got,</l>
                     <l>Downe to obliuion fell;</l>
                     <l>And he for Gantlet (wrapt with Giues)</l>
                     <l>Was brought to second Hell</l>
                     <l>Captiuitie: what should he doe? appeale</l>
                     <l>from Iustice Throne,</l>
                     <l>That bootelesse were, for now his hopes</l>
                     <l>Are fully razed downe.</l>
                     <l>The time approach'd (sad time God wot)</l>
                     <l>When brought vnto the <hi>Barre</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He gaue the Iudge blunt eloquence,</l>
                     <l>Like to a Man of warre:</l>
                     <l>But to be short accus'd he is,</l>
                     <l>What he cannot denie,</l>
                     <l>And therefore by a publike doome</l>
                     <l>He censur'd was to die.</l>
                     <l>But if the Iudge had rightly done,</l>
                     <l>The Captaine (by the way)</l>
                     <l>As he had tane his standing-wage,</l>
                     <l>Should reape his hanging-pay.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:46"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon the death of one<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Martial: in nom. Thet. &amp; Nympham, &amp; pastorem hoc nomine inducit in Elegijs &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigrammat.</note>
                        <hi>Thete</hi> who died, and was cast in a great tempest vpon the Sea, into a straite of that part of the Sea which diuides <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>sia</hi> from <hi>Hellespont.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Here lies <hi>Thete</hi> pale and wan,</l>
                     <l>Buried in the Ocean.</l>
                     <l>More it seemes to augment her fame,</l>
                     <l>Since from Sea shee tooke her Name.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thetis</hi> was <hi>Achilles</hi> mother,</l>
                     <l>Yet of that name there's another</l>
                     <l>To this day record'd by Tyme,</l>
                     <l>That she was a Saint Diuine.</l>
                     <l>Here her Image sleepes in peace,</l>
                     <l>Promising this ile encrease</l>
                     <l>Nere this Fount</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Hellespont.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander</hi> amorous soules,</l>
                     <l>In midst of her greene bosome daily roules;</l>
                     <l>Which to <hi>Abydos</hi> (ancient towne)</l>
                     <l>And to <hi>Cestos</hi> brought renowne,</l>
                     <l>And that shrine</l>
                     <l>So diuine.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:47"/>
                     <l>Where <hi>Paphos</hi> was erected to expresse,</l>
                     <l>There <hi>Hero</hi> was to Venus Ʋotaresse:</l>
                     <l>Rest in honor, <hi>Thete</hi> rest</l>
                     <l>By the Sea-Nymphs euer blest,</l>
                     <l>for they loue</l>
                     <l>to approue</l>
                     <l>The rare condition of that diuine Creature,</l>
                     <l>Where Art is far surpast by spotlesse Nature.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Synon</hi> that villaine which sacked <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Ist possible that wormes dare once conspire</l>
                     <l>"To tutch his shrowde that sackt all <hi>Troy</hi> with fire?</l>
                     <l>O saies poore <hi>Hecuba,</hi> that thou hadst dide</l>
                     <l>Before shee had such fatall obiects spide</l>
                     <l>Of her dislaughter'd Sonnes, weeping to see</l>
                     <l>Mother and issue slau'd to miserie.</l>
                     <l>O saies (old <hi>Priam</hi>) and he teares his haire,</l>
                     <l>Wishing thy Tombe had razed his despaire,</l>
                     <l>When in the ruines of defaced <hi>Troy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in the Gore of his beloued <hi>Boy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His yongling <hi>Troylus,</hi> he wash'd his head</l>
                     <l>In an eternall Concaue buried.</l>
                     <l>Thus does <hi>Troy</hi> curse, yet may thou defend</l>
                     <l>Thy <hi>Proiects,</hi> and the cause of <hi>Troyans</hi> end</l>
                     <l>Proceeding from themselues, thou for the sake</l>
                     <l>Of thy deare Country, and faire <hi>Hellens</hi> rape,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:47"/>
                     <l>Became a <hi>villaine,</hi> and to keepe thy Name,</l>
                     <l>Thou liu'd a <hi>villaine,</hi> and thou died the same.</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>villanie</hi> is dead! in <hi>Synon</hi> true,</l>
                     <l>But he haz left his trade vnto the Iew</l>
                     <l>And English cormorant, who in one houre</l>
                     <l>Desire both Name and Substance to deuoure,</l>
                     <l>Then there's no diffrence: both bring like annoy,</l>
                     <l>Saue th' one for <hi>England</hi> is, th' other for <hi>Troy.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sleepe then in silent slumber, for thy <hi>Race,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In right of their succession take thy place.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Argus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Argus</hi> with his hundred eies,</l>
                     <l>Eie-lesse in this Coffin lies;</l>
                     <l>While Wormes keepe their Sessions there,</l>
                     <l>Where once Lamps of eye-sight were.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <l>Earth feedes on me, that once fed me,</l>
                     <l>Court begot me, Country bred me;</l>
                     <l>Thus my death preuents my youth,</l>
                     <l>Bastard slippes haue slowest growth.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon Gold a dissolute Hackster.</head>
                     <l>Gold, th'art a knaue; and drainst thy golden showre,</l>
                     <l>Not from the lap of <hi>Danaë,</hi> but thy whoore;</l>
                     <l>Leaue thy base Panders trade, make speede, reuolt</l>
                     <l>From so deform'd a standard; who would be boult</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:48"/>
                     <l>To his wifes lewdnesse, or expresse his shame,</l>
                     <l>By vshering the ruine of his name</l>
                     <l>For money? ceasse, ceasse to be impudent,</l>
                     <l>Transplant thy selfe to some pure element</l>
                     <l>More wholesome and lesse shamefull; liue enrold,</l>
                     <l>And haue thy Name in characters of Gold,</l>
                     <l>That whoso passeth may this Impresse reade:</l>
                     <l>Thy age did end in Gold, begunne in lead.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Quackesaluer Doctors graue in <hi>Venice,</hi> by Transcription we reade this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription as followeth.</head>
                     <l>Heere lies a pound of Rheu-barbe (as't doth seeme)</l>
                     <l>To purge the worms of Choler, Rheume and Fleame:</l>
                     <l>A Dapper Doctor (ill may Fate befall)</l>
                     <l>To take from vs Sir <hi>Ierome Vrinall;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet this our comfort is; though he be dead,</l>
                     <l>Haz left another sauce-fleam'd knaue in's stead.</l>
                     <l>"That can call backe from dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h a breathlesse corse,</l>
                     <l>"And cure his griefe as he doth cure a horse</l>
                     <l>Farewell Sir <hi>Ierome,</hi> thou with horse began,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Don</hi> begins with Horse, and ends with Man.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Croesus</hi> and <hi>Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Twixt <hi>Croesus</hi> and <hi>Irus</hi> difference I know none,</l>
                     <l>Saue <hi>Irus</hi> haz no Tombe, <hi>Croesus</hi> haz one.</l>
                     <l>Nor skills is much what shrowding sheet they wore,</l>
                     <l>"For I nere heardth as worm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the shrowd forbore:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:48"/>
                     <l>Because the pompe or state wherein they laide,</l>
                     <l>Might by their terror make poore wormes afraide.</l>
                     <l>But as on earth great ones did feed on small,</l>
                     <l>"So worms do feed on great ones most of all.</l>
                     <l>Do well then while we liue; for being dead,</l>
                     <l>"Or Fame or Shame our Actions merit meade.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Delia.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Thou <hi>Delos</hi>-sacred-chaste inhabitant,</l>
                     <l>For of thy followers <hi>Albion</hi> haz but scant;</l>
                     <l>Plant (pray thee heere) some house religiously,</l>
                     <l>Where we may reuerence spotlesse Chastitie:</l>
                     <l>For since thy ship did from this Iland lance,</l>
                     <l>"Best gifts we had were fire<note n="*" place="margin">In adagium habentur pyrobalae Galliae.</note> balls sent from <hi>France.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Coole vs this Climate that seemes to aspire,</l>
                     <l>Not by her owne, but by a forraine fire,</l>
                     <l>That now at last the <hi>Albionact</hi> may know,</l>
                     <l>Th' <hi>Delian</hi> our friend, thogh th' Frenchmē be our foe:</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>In Mydam.</head>
                     <l>Miser nemini est bonus, sibi pessimus.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mydas</hi> would feed on gold (vnhappy wretch)</l>
                     <l>That starues himselfe, to make himselfe more rich,</l>
                     <l>'Tis like a painted couer that conueies</l>
                     <l>Each sparkeling obiect to our piersing eies,</l>
                     <l>Which while the eies delight in, they grow dim,</l>
                     <l>Euen so it fares (poore miser) still with him.</l>
                     <l>"He feeds on gold, for there's his hearts delight:</l>
                     <l>But that same obiect takes away his sight,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:49"/>
                     <l>And makes him duskie eide, clouded and blinde,</l>
                     <l>Though not in body, yet in th' eyes of minde:</l>
                     <l>Then this shall stand fixt on the misers boure,<note place="margin">His Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>"He liued rich (to th' eye) but truly poore.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nec copia nec inopia minuitur. Salust.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>In <hi>Veprem</hi> Iuridicum.</head>
                     <l>Heere lies <hi>Brier</hi> a Lawyer true,</l>
                     <l>Yet no true Lawyer, giue him's due:</l>
                     <l>His cause of sickenesse (as I heare)</l>
                     <l>Was: There's but foure Terms in the yeare.</l>
                     <l>But others thinke (and so they may)</l>
                     <l>Because he could not long delay</l>
                     <l>His Clients suite, yong <hi>Had-lands</hi> cause,</l>
                     <l>Which hauing got into his clawes,</l>
                     <l>He by renewing of their strife,</l>
                     <l>Thought to keep't for terme of life.</l>
                     <l>But <hi>AEacus</hi> that god of warre,</l>
                     <l>Pitcht me this Lawyer ouer-barre.</l>
                     <l>So in despaire (vnhappy elfe)</l>
                     <l>The Lawyer went and hang'd himselfe.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Broaker.</head>
                     <l>Heere lies a Broaker of <hi>Long-lane,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who by <hi>Pick-hatch</hi> &amp; <hi>Hounsditch</hi> got infinit gaine:</l>
                     <l>The Pyrats of <hi>Wapping</hi> were likewise his friends,</l>
                     <l>Requeathing to him their clothes at their ends.</l>
                     <l>"O hard-hearted death, more cruell then any,</l>
                     <l>That would not be mou'd at the <hi>sutes</hi> of so many!</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:49"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Heere lies an old <hi>Concealer</hi> vnderneath,</l>
                     <l>Who hardly could <hi>conceale</hi> himselfe from death.</l>
                     <l>"Thus though man be disguis'd in varied formes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Conceal'd</hi> on earth, yet not <hi>conceal'd</hi> from worms,</l>
                     <l>Thou then that passest by this seely wretch,</l>
                     <l>"This morall may experience <hi>thee</hi> teach;</l>
                     <l>There's nought so hid, which in Earths bosome lyes,</l>
                     <l>"Put fate (with pierciue eyes) looks through &amp; spies.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Holofornus</hi> an vnconscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Vsurer.</head>
                     <l>Within this Grate lies one <hi>Holofernus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His bodie's</hi> in earth: but his soule in <hi>Auernus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"Vnder his head lies a bagge of red gold,</l>
                     <l>Which both heart and <hi>conscience</hi> together enfold.</l>
                     <l>See worm-holes are sprouting, which seems to expres,</l>
                     <l>They loath to feede on an Ʋsurers flesh.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Gnat.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Sleepe on poore <hi>Gnat,</hi> Gnat was thy proper name,</l>
                     <l>"And thou as properly exprest the same;</l>
                     <l>No difference 'twixt thee buried and before,</l>
                     <l>"Saue that in death thou sleepes, in life didst snore.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:50"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon an Actor now of late deceased: and vpon his Action <hi>Tu quo{que}:</hi> and first vpon his Trauell.</head>
                     <l>Hee whom this mouldered clod of earth doth hide,</l>
                     <l>New come from Sea, made but one face and dide.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vpon his Creditors.</head>
                     <l>His debters now, no fault with him can finde,</l>
                     <l>Sith he has paid to nature, all's behinde.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vnto his fellow Actors.</head>
                     <l>What can you craue of your poore fellow more?</l>
                     <l>"He does but what <hi>Tu quoque</hi> did before:</l>
                     <l>Then giue him dying, Actions <hi>second wreath,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"That second'd him in Action and in death.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon Loues champion.</head>
                     <l>Once did I liue and loue, not loue, but <hi>lust,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in loues turnament perform'd my<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <l>Meerely resembling that wanton Amorist in <hi>Horace,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Vixi puellis nuper idoneus,</l>
                           <l>Et militaui non sine gloria.</l>
                        </note>
                        <hi>iust;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But now return'd I am, whereto all must,</l>
                     <l>Rendring my life, loue, lust and all to <hi>dust.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:50"/>
                     <head>¶ Amor<note n="*" place="margin">This inscripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on writ vpon the tombe of a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Patrician of Rome, and may be transcribed, vnto one of ours no lesse memorable for eminence of place, and since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> viuat &amp; crescat honor, inuitis fatis resurgat virtus, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geatur pietas, &amp; foueatur sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas: altera harum miserijs sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenimus, altera Reip. saluti prouide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Corpus vt perijt, creuit virtus.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Vertue that vs'd to sit enthron'd in state,</l>
                        <l>"In purple cloathed, not in purple sin,</l>
                        <l>Lies heere interr'd, for shee's enshrin'd in him,</l>
                        <l>Not prun'd as vicious men, by common fate,</l>
                        <l>For vertue is of higher estimate</l>
                        <l>Then to subscribe to times abridged date;</l>
                        <l>Nor can the clowde of Enuie, honour dim,</l>
                        <l>For when shee seemes to die, shee does begin</l>
                        <l>"To raise her glory higher then before,</l>
                        <l>Immortaliz'd in Heauen, for euermore.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>An happy passage, happy pilgrimage,</l>
                        <l>"Where our Earths conflict wins eternitie,</l>
                        <l>Securest harbour of tranquilitie,</l>
                        <l>To passe from Earth to Heauen, where mutually</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:51"/>
                        <l>The Saints of God reioice, free from the rage</l>
                        <l>Of sinnes assaults, or of this fleshly cage,</l>
                        <l>Wherein we are enthrald: distressed age</l>
                        <l>
                           <note n="*" place="bottom">Nihil turpius est quam grandis natu Senex, qui nullum aliud argumentum, quo se probat diu vixisse, quam aetatem habet. Senec. de Tranq. anim.</note>That makes vs old in nought saue miserie:</l>
                        <l>"But pilgrims, if for Christ perplexed be,</l>
                        <l>Shall liue with him in ioy perpetually.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thrice blessed pilgrime, that hast spent thy daies</l>
                        <l>In the promoting of thy Countries weale,</l>
                        <l>Faithfull in all, wherein thou wast to deale,</l>
                        <l>Shoaring vpon thy shoulders those decaies,</l>
                        <l>Which seem'd to ruinate the state alwaies;</l>
                        <l>These blessed actions do deserued due praise,</l>
                        <l>Triumphant patron of the common-weale:</l>
                        <l>Who <hi>(though she should)</hi> vnthankefully conceale</l>
                        <l>"Those many vertues which thy minde possest,</l>
                        <l>Thou needs not feare: <hi>in Heauen they are exprest.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>True Register, where all thy acts remaine</l>
                        <l>In perfect colours liuely shadowed,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>map of honour,</hi> well decyphered,</l>
                        <l>Where innocence receiues immortall gaine</l>
                        <l>For her pure life, polluted with no staine</l>
                        <l>Of earths allurements: <hi>Earth</hi> cannot containe</l>
                        <l>A vertuous minde, for it will still aspire</l>
                        <l>To <hi>Syons</hi> hill, ascending euer higher,</l>
                        <l>Till shee discerne the fruits of her pure loue,</l>
                        <l>By leauing earth to liue in Courts aboue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:51"/>
                        <l>Thou that art here immur'd with barres of earth,</l>
                        <l>"Returning to the place from whence thou came,</l>
                        <l>Shall by thy death perpetuate thy Name:</l>
                        <l>"Sith forraine Coasts haue much admir'd the same;</l>
                        <l>And though thy foes, yet they extoll'd thy worth,</l>
                        <l>"Being twice noble in <hi>thy selfe, thy birth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which no succeeding times shall ere raze forth.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>"Honour will euer flourish, as it was</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Though not engrauen in faire leaues of brasse.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For what is Brasse, Marble, or Iuorie?</l>
                        <l>What will auaile the Monuments of time,</l>
                        <l>When those they represent, seeme to decline</l>
                        <l>In the Worlds eye? in whom our memorie</l>
                        <l>Liues, or lies dead: O then liue vertuouslie,</l>
                        <l>That winnes a Crowne here, and eternallie.</l>
                        <l>Worlds respects a blast, a bud a flower,</l>
                        <l>Now sprouting faire, &amp; blasted in an houre;</l>
                        <l>But who shall flourish in the <hi>Sacred Groue,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>"Shall ere stand firme, his Scyons cannot moue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Liue in this Hearse: Death to the good's no death,</l>
                        <l>"But a transportance from a Sea of woes</l>
                        <l>To future ioyes, from shipwracke to repose:</l>
                        <l>For such as these, God for himselfe doth choose,</l>
                        <l>Clipping their Temples with a golden wreath,</l>
                        <l>Infusing in their soules eternall breath:</l>
                        <l>Thrice blessed vine that in heau'ns Vineyard growes,</l>
                        <l>Whose spreading branches farre more beauty showes</l>
                        <l>
                           <note n="*" place="bottom">Fulgebunt iusti vt stèllae. Quem autem putat in eorum mentibus si tantum in eorum corporibus splendorem illuxisse videris? Vid. August. in Man.</note>Then Sun or Moone, or th' purest Element;</l>
                        <l>Or any Starre within the Firmament.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:52"/>
                        <l>Such trees we see bring forth the ripest fruit,</l>
                        <l>As planted are vpon the waters side,</l>
                        <l>Whose liquid streames their neighbour bankes diuide:</l>
                        <l>Euen so where <hi>Springs</hi> of diuine grace doe glide,</l>
                        <l>The seeds of Vertue take the deepest roote,</l>
                        <l>Where euery sprig both bloome and fruit sends out</l>
                        <l>A Glorious <hi>Haruest:</hi> which what ere betide,</l>
                        <l>Is not by stormes dismaide, but fructifide.</l>
                        <l>Such goodly trees are plants of <hi>Paradise,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which bring forth fruit in such varieties.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And such a tree art thou, whose noble stem</l>
                        <l>Did nourish Learning, &amp; <hi>Mineruas</hi> friends:</l>
                        <l>Thy flowrie blossome in their growth extends,</l>
                        <l>And after death some fruitfull gleanings sends</l>
                        <l>From Heauen aboue to Earths-suruiuing men,</l>
                        <l>That seeing them, might seeke to follow them;</l>
                        <l>But most to such as 'bout the Court attends,</l>
                        <l>That vertuous liues may weaue their glorious ends.</l>
                        <l>"For Ʋertue was as <hi>Ariadnes</hi> thread</l>
                        <l>"That led the liuing, and empales the dead.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>What hissing Serpent with her venemous sting</l>
                        <l>Can hurt thy vertues which be registred</l>
                        <l>In Heauen aboue? where th'art canonized</l>
                        <l>And with the fruits of vertue garnished;</l>
                        <l>Shining for euer with the supreame King</l>
                        <l>Of glorious <hi>Sion:</hi> where the <hi>Angels sing</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hymns</hi> of delight: whose Quires are polished</l>
                        <l>With Saphires, Emeralds: replenished</l>
                        <l>With springs still flowing full of sweet delight,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:52"/>
                        <l>Not cross'd by shadowes of a gloom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ight.</l>
                        <l>"If we be Pilgrims here (as sure we be)</l>
                        <l>"Why should we loue to liue, and liue to die?</l>
                        <l>"If Earthen Vessels, why should we relie</l>
                        <l>"With such assurance on our frailtie?</l>
                        <l>"Since greatest States doe perish soon'st we see,</l>
                        <l>"And rich and poore haue one communitie</l>
                        <l>"In th' eyes of Fate: nor could I ere espie</l>
                        <l>"In humaine state, ought saue inconstancie.</l>
                        <l>"Times follow Times, motion admits no rest,</l>
                        <l>"But in this motion,<note n="*" place="bottom">Hei mihi, quod non est Tempus vt ante fuit. &amp;c. Ouid. Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra temporibus succedunt pessima primis.</note> worst succeede the best.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If loue be said to liue, honour encrease,</l>
                        <l>Or Ʋertue flourish in despite of Fate,</l>
                        <l>I neede not feare this noble <hi>Heroes</hi> state,</l>
                        <l>Though much pursu'd (as't seemes) by publike hate,</l>
                        <l>His Ship is harbour'd in the Port of peace:</l>
                        <l>Where times-succeeding ioyes shall neuer cease;</l>
                        <l>Great are they sure which none can explicate,</l>
                        <l>And great in worth, which none can estimate.</l>
                        <l>Thus great on Earth, and great in Heauen together,</l>
                        <l>Ʋertue with greatnes, makes him heire of either.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let this same Epitaph I consecrate</l>
                        <l>Ʋnto thy Noble-<hi>Hearse,</hi> expresse my loue</l>
                        <l>And duty both: (for both doe me behoue;)</l>
                        <l>"If of my poore endeuours thou approue.</l>
                        <l>These lines be th' obsequies I dedicate,</l>
                        <l>Which though they come like <hi>Seede</hi> that's sowen too late;</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:53"/>
                        <l>Yet some in due compassion they may moue,</l>
                        <l>To plant more cheerefull tendrells in thy <hi>Groue.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>"<hi>Honour</hi> attend thy presence (famous Herse)</l>
                        <l>"Too much obscur'd by my impolisht verse.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Epitaph.</head>
                     <l>Mortis vbi stimulus? pro me tulit omnia Christus:</l>
                     <l>"Consul eram primo tempore, Consul ero.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ode">
                     <head>¶ A funerall Ode.</head>
                     <l>O thou heauen-aspiring Spirit,</l>
                     <l>Resting on thy Sauiours merit!</l>
                     <l>liue in peace,</l>
                     <l>for encrease</l>
                     <l>Blest this Iland in thy being:</l>
                     <l>Mindes vnited still agreeing.</l>
                     <l>Peace possest thee,</l>
                     <l>Peace hath blest thee.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Halcyon</hi> dayes be where thou dwellest,</l>
                     <l>"As in Glorie thou excellest.</l>
                     <l>Death by dying,</l>
                     <l>Life enioying.</l>
                     <l>Richer fraight was nere obtained,</l>
                     <l>Then thy Pilgrim-steps haue gained.</l>
                     <l>Blessed pleasure,</l>
                     <l>happy Treasure.</l>
                     <l>Thus many distinct ioyes in one exprest,</l>
                     <l>Say to thy Soule, <hi>Come Soule and take thy rest.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:53"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon the death of the <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuously affected S<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                        </hi> Thomas Boin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, a Knight so wel-meriting, as <hi>his vertues farre aboue all</hi> Titles, enstiled him worthy the <hi>loue of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Sad shadie<note n="*" place="margin">Meaning a shadie tuft of trees adioyning to Hannaby his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-house.</note>
                        <hi>Groue,</hi> how faire so ere thou show,</l>
                     <l>"Reft art thou of thy <hi>Teare-bath'd maister</hi> now:</l>
                     <l>Yet grow thou shalt; and mai'st in time to come,</l>
                     <l>With thy shed-leaues shadow thy Maisters tombe,</l>
                     <l>Which is adorn'd with this Inscription:</l>
                     <l>"Weepe Marble, weepe, for losse of <hi>Bointon:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet he's not lost; for as the Scripture saith,</l>
                     <l>"That is not lost (for certaine) which God hath.</l>
                     <l>Ceasse <hi>Ladie</hi> then with teares your eies to dim,</l>
                     <l>"He must not come to <hi>You,</hi> but you to <hi>Him.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:54"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon that memorable Act atchieued by an Auncestour of the <hi>Cogniers</hi> in the discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiture of a <hi>Winged-worme</hi> or <hi>Snake,</hi> Whose approach was no lesse obuious then mortally dangerous to the distressed Passenger; His Monument remaineth in the body of the church at<note n="*" place="margin">Antiquae &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis familiae de Cogn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ers domici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. Camd. in Britann.</note>
                        <hi>Sockburn,</hi> where hee lieth crosse-legged, (which inferreth his being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Conquest</hi>) hauing his Fauchion by his side, his Dogge at his feete, Grasping with the <hi>Snake,</hi> the <hi>Snake</hi> with the <hi>Dogge:</hi> the renowmed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of which Act addeth no lesse glory to the houses Antiquitie, then the worthy<note n="*" place="margin">Meaning Sir <hi>Iohn Cogniers,</hi> now deceased, a Knight no lesse generous then gracious in the eye of his <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey.</hi>
                        </note> Knight who now possesseth it, gaineth harts by his affability.</head>
                     <l>Colle sub exigu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> iacuit canis, vnde peremit</l>
                     <l>Aligerum vermem, quo sibi fama venit.</l>
                     <l>Quo sibi Fama venit, veniet, semper{que} manebit,</l>
                     <l>Sidera dum coeli, gramina tellus habent.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:54"/>
                     <head>Paraphrastically translated.</head>
                     <l>Vpon a hill his Gray-hound lay, till that his Maister blew</l>
                     <l>His writhed horne, at whose approach the winged Worme he slew:</l>
                     <l>Whēce Fame gaue wings to <hi>Cogniers</hi> name which euer shalbe giuē</l>
                     <l>So long as grasse growes on the earth, or stars appeare in heauen.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vpon his Tombe.</head>
                     <l>Who slew the Worme is now worms meat, yet hope assures me hence,</l>
                     <l>Who th'worme ore-threwhe after slew, the worme of Conscience.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Epitaphs vpon diuerse of the <hi>Sages</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> translated, omitting <hi>Thales</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi> and beginning with the rest, original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traduced from <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertius.</hi> Vpon <hi>Chylo.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Thankes to the blushing morne that first begunne</l>
                     <l>To decke the Laureat brow of <hi>Chyloes</hi> sonne,</l>
                     <l>Which He (old-man) as ouer-ioy'd to see,</l>
                     <l>Fell dead through Ioy; I wish like death to me.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>This Inscription also was engrauen on his Tombe.</head>
                     <l>Heere <hi>Chylo</hi> lies, in <hi>Lacedemon</hi> bred,</l>
                     <l>Who 'mongst the <hi>Seuen</hi> was rightly numbred.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:55"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Pittucus,</hi> whose Tombe was erected by the Citie <hi>Lesbos</hi> wherein he liued; beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with this inscription to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate his memory.</head>
                     <l>Within this Tombe doth <hi>Lesbos thee</hi> enshrine,</l>
                     <l>Drencht with their teares and consecrate as thine.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Bias</hi> whom <hi>Priene</hi> with all solemnitie and magnificence, at their owne proper cost in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred: Engrauing these verses vpon his Tombe, for the continuance of his Name.</head>
                     <l>This well-wrought stone doth <hi>Bias</hi> corps containe,</l>
                     <l>Who was an honour to th' <hi>Ionian:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pleading his friends cause (as a faithfull friend)</l>
                     <l>Pausing to take his breath, <hi>He breath'd</hi> his end.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Cleobulus,</hi> who was buried in <hi>Lyndus,</hi> which boundeth on the Sea-cliffe; the situ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation whereof is shadowed in this inscription vpon his Tombe.</head>
                     <l>That wise <hi>Cleobulus</hi> should extinguish'd be,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lyndus</hi> laments enuiron'd with the Sea;</l>
                     <l>So as two Seas neere <hi>Lyndus</hi> strand arise,</l>
                     <l>"A <hi>Leuant Sea,</hi> a <hi>Sea in Lyndus eies.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:55"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon <hi>Periander</hi> of Corinth was this Epitaph ensuing found to be engrauen, which through the iniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie of time, and want of Art in the impressure, was so defaced, as by the testimonie of <hi>Laertius</hi> it could scarce be reduced to <hi>Sence:</hi> yet now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Originall faithfully translated, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding a Christian resolution in a Pagans dissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reposing a more true happines in his end then in his Birth, his <hi>exit</hi> or passage, then his <hi>intrat</hi> to this Theatre or transitorie Pilgrimage: making his <hi>diem fatalem,</hi> his <hi>diem natalem,</hi> the day of his <hi>death</hi> the day of his <hi>birth;</hi> where <hi>Man</hi> by an imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue goodnesse, deduced from God not inherent in himselfe, may in his <hi>death</hi> be rather said to be translated then departed.</head>
                     <l>Corinth both wise and rich in treasures store,</l>
                     <l>Keepes <hi>Perianders</hi> Bodie in her shore.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Continued by <hi>Laertius</hi> by way of an <hi>Epigram,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Greeue not that <hi>Thou</hi> shouldst not obtaine thy wish,</l>
                     <l>But ioy in that the Gods haue giuen thee this,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Thou</hi> by death hast past <hi>those sorrowes</hi> now,</l>
                     <l>Which many one would doe, but cannot doe.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:56"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon the much lamented death of the truly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable (eminent patterne of vnblemished Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice) Sir <hi>Augustine Nicholls</hi> one of our Iudges of the Northerne Circuit, who died at <hi>Kendall</hi> the third day of August, <hi>Anno</hi> 1616.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sic Nicholaus obit, potius Nicodemus, &amp; astra</l>
                        <l>nunc Astraea petit, quae moriendo tenet.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nicholls</hi> is dead, or <hi>Nicodemus</hi> rather,</l>
                        <l>The Widdows cheerer, and the Orphans father;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dead!</hi> why it cannot be Iustice should die,</l>
                        <l>For she ha's will and power enough to flie</l>
                        <l>Aboue the reach of Death. It's true, yet Death</l>
                        <l>Hath reft this Iustice-patron of his breath:</l>
                        <l>Of Breath? No matter, Breath is but a winde</l>
                        <l>That vades, but cannot preiudice the Minde</l>
                        <l>Where Iustice sits as <hi>Regent:</hi> wherefore then</l>
                        <l>Since Iustice liues, should she be mon'd by men</l>
                        <l>As if deceast? Ile tell you, <hi>Heere is one,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Or was one rather,</hi> for he now is gone,</l>
                        <l>Who seeing th'end of Iustice-circuit nie,</l>
                        <l>Embracing Death, did in his <hi>Circuit</hi> die;</l>
                        <l>No maruell then if men do Iustice mone,</l>
                        <l>When <hi>They</hi> do find her mansion vnder stone:</l>
                        <l>And hard it is to finde <hi>Her</hi> whom <hi>They</hi> seeke,</l>
                        <l>As t' heare the stone that couers <hi>her</hi> to speake.</l>
                        <l>"This then shall be her <hi>Dirge,</hi> her dying Song,</l>
                        <l>"She pleads in heauen, on earth she ha's lost her tong.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Terras Astraea reliquit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:56"/>
                     <head>Another Dialogue-wise: <hi>Eubaeus</hi> and <hi>Tymaeus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Silence, awake not Iustice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Who can keepe</l>
                        <l>the eies of Iustice closed?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Death and Sleepe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Death cannot do it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Cannot! pray thee see</l>
                        <l>What Death hath done then.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>"Lasse! how mortally</l>
                        <l>lies Iustice wounded?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Wounded! no, shee's dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Dead!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes; see tong, pulse, arme, eie, heart, hand, head.</l>
                        <l>all motionlesse; come nearer:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>I'me too near.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Doest weepe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>I offer to her Shrine a teare.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou art too childish.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>No, if I could more,</l>
                        <l>I would expresse it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Why, didst nere know before</l>
                        <l>Iustice lie speechlesse?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, but nere did know</l>
                        <l>despaire of her recouery till now.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>No, thou hast heard that saying new</l>
                        <l>growne common.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymaeus.</speaker>
                        <l>What might it be?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:57"/>
                        <speaker>Eubae.</speaker>
                        <l>That <hi>Iustice</hi>'s like a Woman;</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymae.</speaker>
                        <l>In what respect?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubae.</speaker>
                        <l>In this it may bef'ed</l>
                        <l>When <hi>she</hi> lies <hi>speechles, shee</hi> is neerly dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Tymae.</speaker>
                        <l>Most true in both</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eubae.</speaker>
                        <l>It is, but doe not weepe;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let's vanish hence,</hi> &amp; <hi>suffer Iustice sleepe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <head>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Epitaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi formā composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note>¶ An Epitaph reduced to the forme of a Dialogue; consisting of two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and two Parts, representing in the Persons, <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Instruction;</hi> in the Parts Passion and Consolation: prepared at first for the memory of his neuer-sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembred <hi>Father</hi> by the <hi>Authour,</hi> emphatically shadowed vnder the name of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopater.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The Persons names are</hi> Philopater <hi>and</hi> Philogenes.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philop.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sleepes my deare Father?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philoge.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, my Sonne I sleepe:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philop.</speaker>
                        <l>Why, then I wrong'd your quiet rest to weepe;</l>
                        <l>Sith <hi>Christians</hi> should not any difference make</l>
                        <l>Twixt <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Sleepe;</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philoge.</speaker>
                        <l>It's true, for both awake,</l>
                        <l>Both lie them downe, both rise, both bedding haue,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The liuing haue their couch, the dead their graue;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:57"/>
                        <l>For as our <hi>Death</hi> by <hi>Sleepe</hi> is shadowed,</l>
                        <l>So by our <hi>Bed</hi> our <hi>Graue</hi> is measured.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philop.</speaker>
                        <l>O pardon then my teares.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philoge.</speaker>
                        <l>My Sonne I doe,</l>
                        <l>These teares <hi>thou sheds</hi> do thy <hi>affectiō</hi> show,</l>
                        <l>And beare record in Heauen;</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philop.</speaker>
                        <l>Where you are blest:</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philoge.</speaker>
                        <l>Indeede I am.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philop.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Heauens</hi> grant my Soule like rest.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ A Diuine composition, stiled The Pilgrimes Petition.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Keepe me (O Lord) ô daigne my Soule to keep,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou art her</hi> Shepheard, shee the wandring Sheep:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou art the liuing life, the Labourers way;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Pilgrims staffe, Faiths Anchor, Iosuahs day:</l>
                     <l>Yea, Iosuahs Day-starre, who (so if thou please)</l>
                     <l>Canst make the Sun goe backe <hi>without degrees.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ The Sinners Cymball.</head>
                     <l>I cried vnto the Lord, he healed me,</l>
                     <l>I sicke to death, he shew'd me remedie;</l>
                     <l>I hunger-staru'd, he gaue me <hi>Angels</hi> food,</l>
                     <l>I all a thirst, he quench'd it with his blood.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="dialogue">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:58"/>
                     <head>¶ In obitum<note n="*" place="margin">De Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesiade.</note>
                        <hi>Thomae Brathwaite</hi> op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timae spei, indolis generosissimae, vitae probatissimae, fidei integerrimae, omni ex parte parati peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti{que} <hi>R. B.</hi> Memoriae eius studiosissimus lugubria ista Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata grati animi pignora diu meditata &amp; iam serò sed seriò in publicam lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem prolata (Dialogi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re) composuit.</head>
                     <stage>Philaretus and Euthymius.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philaret.</speaker>
                        <p>Quò redis?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Euthym.</speaker>
                        <p>In gremium matris:</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philaret.</speaker>
                        <p>Quos quaeris?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Euthym.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Amicos.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philaret.</speaker>
                        <p>His moriendo cares:</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Euthym.</speaker>
                        <p>His moriendo fruor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philar.</speaker>
                        <p>Tunc tibi mors lucrum:</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Euthym.</speaker>
                        <p>Mihi lux, via, vita, leuamen.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Philar.</speaker>
                        <p>Tunc non amissus;</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Euthy.</speaker>
                        <p>Missus at ante meos.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagram">
                     <head>¶ In Anagramma quod sibi ipsi compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suit &amp; Annulo inscripsit.
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Brathwaite</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Vita vt herba.</item>
                        </list>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vita</hi> vt <hi>Herba</hi> tuum est Anagramma, tua{que} sub vrna</l>
                     <l>Hoc videam, breuis est vita, sed herba leuis,</l>
                     <l>Annulus hoc tenuit, nam{que} Annulus arctus vt annus,</l>
                     <l>Quo (velut afflatu) fata futura refers.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:58"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon the late decease of his much lamented friend and kinsman, <hi>Allen Nicholson,</hi> a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous &amp; industrious member both in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hauxide</hi> laments thy <hi>Death, Grasmyre</hi> not so,</l>
                     <l>Wishing <hi>Thou</hi> hadst beene <hi>dead</hi> ten yeeres agoe;</l>
                     <l>For then her market had not so beene done,</l>
                     <l>But had suruiu'd thy <hi>Age</hi> in time to come:</l>
                     <l>And well may <hi>Hauxide</hi> grieue at thy <hi>Departure,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"Since <hi>Shee</hi> receiu'd from <hi>thee</hi> her ancient <hi>charter,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Grasmyre</hi> sues (since <hi>Thou</hi> art turn'd to <hi>grasse</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To bring about, &amp; now hath broght to passe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus much for thee:</hi> nor would I haue <hi>thee</hi> know it,</l>
                     <l>For thy pure <hi>zeale</hi> could nere endure a <hi>Poet;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet for the <hi>Loue</hi> I bore <hi>thee,</hi> and that <hi>Blood</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which twixt vs both by Natiue course hath flow'd:</l>
                     <l>"This will I say, and may; for sure I am</l>
                     <l>"The <hi>North</hi> nere bred sincerer <hi>Purer man.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ In obitum generosissimi viri <hi>L. P.</hi> genio quàm ingenio minus faelici, <hi>Franciscus Ridgeway</hi> eius memoriae studiosissimus hosce threneticos modos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posuit.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Flebo, cur? amisi memorandi pignus amici,</l>
                        <l>Falleris, amitti morte petente nequit;</l>
                        <l>Praemitti fateor, Quis enim non fata capesset,</l>
                        <l>Discimur exemplo, sic oriendo mori.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:178199:59"/>
                        <l>At dolet exemplis tua fata venisse sub illis,</l>
                        <l>Quëis si tu perias, fama perennis erit.</l>
                        <l>Quid dixi an peries? peries sanè corpore, quid si</l>
                        <l>Hac species periat, mens speciosa manet?</l>
                        <l>Altera pars terram repetat, pars altera coelum,</l>
                        <l>Nec mutas mores caela petendo tuos.</l>
                        <l>At vale, nam faciem neque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> discernere gratam</l>
                        <l>Quae mihi semper erit gratia sed arcta nimis,</l>
                        <l>Arcta nimis sed amaena satis, dum sidera vultum</l>
                        <l>Splendida praestantem continuere tuum.</l>
                        <l>Sic perijt quod terra parit, quod vertice coeli</l>
                        <l>Profluit, in coelum tendat &amp; alta petat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Aliud,</head>
                        <l>Hic situs est Satyrus qui stupra a latere potentum</l>
                        <l>Impatiens, patiens limina mortis adit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Englished,</head>
                        <l>Heere lies a Satyre now reduc'd to dust,</l>
                        <l>Who scourg'd desertlesse honour, great mens lust,</l>
                        <l>These <hi>taxt</hi> He <hi>roundly, and had</hi> vow'd <hi>to doe it</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>More boldly yet, if</hi> He <hi>had liu'd vnto it.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ A Funerall Poeme vpon the death of the hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full yong Gentleman Mast. <hi>Will. Horsey,</hi> who deceased the 24. of <hi>Aprill, Ann. Dom.</hi> 1615.</head>
                     <l>"Plants that transplanted are, haue seldome grouth,</l>
                     <l>Yet fares it otherwise with this <hi>blest youth,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:59"/>
                     <l>For <hi>he</hi> transplanted to another Sphere,</l>
                     <l>Perfects that tender grouth which <hi>he</hi> had her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>Tender indeed; yet methinks there appeares</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Age</hi> in his <hi>houres,</hi> though <hi>youth</hi> was in his <hi>yeares,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For</hi> by <hi>experience,</hi> of this sure <hi>I am,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"<hi>Neuer came childe more neere vnto a Man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Well may we then excuse his <hi>mothers</hi> mone,</l>
                     <l>To lose her <hi>Sonne</hi> and that her <hi>onely One,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whose hope gaue life vnto her house and her,</l>
                     <l>"(If mothers erre in this <hi>they</hi> lightly erre)</l>
                     <l>For natiue loue must needs enforce a teare</l>
                     <l>To see <hi>them</hi> laid on <hi>Beare</hi> whom they did beare:</l>
                     <l>To see their Birth turn'd <hi>Earth,</hi> their very wombe</l>
                     <l>Which brought them forth conuerted to a Tombe;</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>this</hi> should make his mother change her song,</l>
                     <l>To see her <hi>hope translat'd</hi>'boue <hi>hope</hi> so yong,</l>
                     <l>To see her onely and now happy <hi>Sonne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To haue his <hi>Pilgrime-taske</hi> so quickly done;</l>
                     <l>But <hi>shee ha's lost him;</hi> no, <hi>he is not lost,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"For where <hi>He</hi> seemes to lose <hi>He</hi> gaineth <hi>most:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And though <hi>He</hi> haue not <hi>Her, He ha's</hi> another,</l>
                     <l>"<hi>For</hi> now the <hi>Church triumphant</hi> is his <hi>Mother</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Feeding his infant-glory with her pap,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dandling him</hi> sweetely in her heauenly lap,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>this</hi> is confirm'd by the <hi>sacred</hi> word,</l>
                     <l>"<hi>He cannot die that dieth in the Lord.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cease then <hi>thou tender Mother,</hi> cease to weepe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy Sonne's</hi> not dead, but onely falne <hi>asleepe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which <hi>sleepe</hi> dissolu'd, his corps shall be vnited</l>
                     <l>Vnto his soule <hi>amongst</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> delighted.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:60"/>
                     <l>"Peace happy Soule crowne thy eternall daies</l>
                     <l>"With wreath of glory to thy <hi>Makers</hi> praise,</l>
                     <l>"<hi>That as thou liu'd a Mirror to thy Age,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"<hi>So thou</hi> may shine in <hi>Sions</hi> heritage.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>His Epitaph.</head>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Orimur &amp; Morimur.</note>Heere interred in this Tombe,</l>
                     <l>Yong, yet vertues hopefull Bloome,</l>
                     <l>Fathers Boy,</l>
                     <l>Mothers ioy</l>
                     <l>Shrined is; yet from this shrine,</l>
                     <l>There's a substance, that's diuine,</l>
                     <l>Which no graue</l>
                     <l>Can receaue:</l>
                     <l>Making claime to Heauens pure clime.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ The Author vpon his selected and euer to be remembred <hi>E. C. Parragon</hi> for beautie and vertue: who died the 5. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb. Ann. Dom.</hi> 1615.</head>
                     <l>Take mother Earth thy virgin-daughter heere,</l>
                     <l>Borne on her Bere ere shee was borne to beare;</l>
                     <l>Take her, for of her wonders may be said,</l>
                     <l>"Heere one and twentie lies who di'de a <hi>Maid.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:60"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon the much lamented <hi>Death</hi> of the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous virgine <hi>A. T.</hi> in <hi>Scarborough,</hi> lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased, and of her sorrowfull Parents incessantly moned.</head>
                     <l>Dead; say no more shee's dead, keepe in that word,</l>
                     <l>It will goe neere to drowne her teare-swolne <hi>Foord:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Why, <hi>He must</hi> know it; true, yet such as <hi>these</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(If grieues)</hi> should be imparted by degrees;</l>
                     <l>How must <hi>they</hi> be imparted? By her <hi>Tombe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It cannot speake; <hi>Such grieues</hi> are seldome dumbe.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Vpon her Tombe.</head>
                     <l>Weepe, weepe <hi>Rosemarie sprig</hi> and <hi>shew</hi> remorce,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou</hi> shold haue deckt her <hi>bride</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">For neere the time appointed for her Bridall, was the day of her Buriall, making way no doubt by her earthly Funerall to a heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Nuptiall.</note> now decks her corse</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon the Tombe of ..... lately erected.</head>
                     <l>..... Perhaps <hi>thou</hi> may haue <hi>Shebnaes</hi> doome,</l>
                     <l>To haue thy corps deuided from thy <hi>Tombe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And haue name of that crest thou gaue thy Neighbor</l>
                     <l>To close thy corps in <hi>Earth,</hi> and saue this labor.</l>
                     <l>How fond then <hi>thou,</hi> to build so costly <hi>Shrine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Neither (perchance) for<note n="*" place="bottom">
                           <l>
                              <hi>This Martiall shadowes vnder the title of</hi> Hermus,</l>
                           <l>Sic tibi nec tumulum conde nec Herme tuis.</l>
                        </note>
                        <hi>thee</hi> nor none of <hi>thine?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet if <hi>thou</hi> want <hi>thy Tombe, thou shalt not misse</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To haue thy <hi>Epitaph, and this it is:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>....... Is <hi>Dead: The cause if you</hi> would know,</l>
                     <l>His winde-pipe burst, and he no more could blow.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:61"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a late deceased Pinch-gut.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Macer</hi> dide rich <hi>they say,</hi> but it's not so,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>he dide</hi> poore, and was indebted too:</l>
                     <l>How should that be? Obserue me, and Ile tell ye</l>
                     <l>He dide indebted both to backe and belly:</l>
                     <l>For all he scrap't from his <hi>Atturnies Fees,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Seru'd but to starue his Maw with bread <hi>&amp;</hi> cheese;</l>
                     <l>So as'mongst those we rightly may him call,</l>
                     <l>Whose life spent lesse then did his <hi>Funerall:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For all his life,</hi> his House scarse eate <hi>one Beast,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>Dead, his Sonne</hi> makes vp the <hi>Churles Feast.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ This the Authour wrote vpon an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Bowler and his Friend, aptly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling Mans life to a game at Bowles.</head>
                     <l>The World is the <hi>Alley</hi> where we play,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Bowles</hi> we play with, Creatures that we vse;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Rubs the Passions</hi> of our minds, the way</l>
                     <l>Needs no <hi>Ground-giuer,</hi> there's but one to chuse</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The way of all Flesh: Seauen's our Game</hi> we say,</l>
                     <l>(<hi>For Seauen yeere is liues-lease</hi> that limits <hi>vs</hi>)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Blocke our end,</hi> which when it draweth on,</l>
                     <l>We poake our <hi>Bowles,</hi> and so our <hi>Game</hi> is done.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:61"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon a singular Irishman.</head>
                     <l>By him lies heere, I finde from whence we came,</l>
                     <l>Where we must goe, how life's an Irish game,</l>
                     <l>This day in health and wealth, next <hi>poore</hi> &amp; <hi>sicke,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"For <hi>Irish</hi> games haue still an <hi>Irish tricke.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon the death of one <hi>Cookes</hi> wife, an Inscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion allusiue to her name.</head>
                     <q>
                        <l>Death's the cooke prouideth meate,</l>
                        <l>For the crawling wormes to eate;</l>
                        <l>Why shouldst thou then <hi>Cooke</hi> repine</l>
                        <l>Death should dresse that wife of thine?</l>
                        <l>All must die, yea time will be,</l>
                        <l>Thou wilt thinke he pleasur'd thee;</l>
                        <l>For no question, being told,</l>
                        <l>She was saplesse, toothlesse, old,</l>
                        <l>He thought fit she'sd liue no longer,</l>
                        <l>That thou might chuse out a yonger.</l>
                        <l>This then on her Age thy youth</l>
                        <l>May be writ as grounded truth,</l>
                        <l>"Heere she lies, long may she lie,</l>
                        <l>"Ere she dide, was wish'd to die.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>This the Author presently composed vpon this occasion; being with sundry Gentlemen at <hi>Walt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> exceeding merrily disposed, one <hi>Cooke</hi> a neighbour of the Hoasts where he lay, came sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly in, pitteously lamenting the death of his
<pb facs="tcp:178199:62"/> wife, being newly departed: euery one laboured to allay his sorrow; but by how much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant were their comforts, by so much more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent were his Passions: at last the Author percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by his Hoast that he expressed a dissembling sorrow, being impatient of her life, and therefore (by all probabilitie) inwardly content with her death, being an old decrepite woman, and He in the Prime of his age, in stead of all vnnecessarie comforts, applied this soueraigne Discourse as a salue to his griefe, without further premeditation.</p>
                     <q>
                        <l>— coenae fercula nostrae</l>
                        <l>Mallem conuinis, quam placuisse cocis.</l>
                     </q>
                     <p>Englished:
<q>
                           <l>As in my choise of meate so in my Booke,</l>
                           <l>I'd rather please my guests, then please my Cooke.</l>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ In Actorem Mimicum cui vix parem cerni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus superstitem;</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quaecun{que} orta sunt occidunt. Salust.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ver vireat quod te peperit (viridissima proles)</l>
                        <l>Quae{que} tegit cineres, ipsa virescat humus.</l>
                        <l>Transis ab exiguis nunquam periture th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>atri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                        <l>Vt repetas sacri pulchra Theatra Iouis.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:62"/>
                     <head>¶ In vultum incredibili lepore respersum.</head>
                     <l>O fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s mutata nimis; spectacula praebes</l>
                     <l>Vermibus, ingenuis saepe probata viris.</l>
                     <l>Quo mutata tuae magis est Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stantia formae,</l>
                     <l>Integra nunc remanet quae peritura fuit.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Vita vt mimus.</head>
                     <l>Exit vt exegit soboles lepidissima partem,</l>
                     <l>Pramia fert hominum, sed meliora Deûm.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Traueller, who taking Inne in a vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage at the signe of the Boore was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably murdered by his Hoast.</head>
                     <l>The brutish-brisled Bore that was my Signe,</l>
                     <l>Where th'Hoast (Bore-like) shed this poore bloud of mine.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Ibidem.</head>
                     <l>An crudelis Aper magis, an crudeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r Hosp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</l>
                     <l>Nescio; saeuus Aper, saeuus &amp; Hospes erat.</l>
                     <l>At saeuus magis Hospes erat, nam conuenit vrsis</l>
                     <l>Inter se sauis, non Hospes ab Hospite tut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>Englished.</head>
                     <l>Whether the Bore or Hoast more cruell be,</l>
                     <l>Cruell the Bore, the Hoast as fierce as He,</l>
                     <l>I know not: but the Hoast's the cruellest:</l>
                     <l>"Beares do agree, while the Hoast betraies his Guest:</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:63"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon certaine Bones found of late buried in the ground, supposed to be some murder commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Hoast, in whose yard these Bones were found; but as yet only suspition is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, no apparancie of Fact discouered.</head>
                     <l>Brow'd be thy hands in bloud, although Thou be</l>
                     <l>Free to the world, thy <hi>Conscience</hi> is not free;</l>
                     <l>For these drie Bones lie mouldred now in Dust,</l>
                     <l>Will manifest thy guilt, for God is iust.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Vpon murder.</head>
                     <l>Murder may seeme to sleepe, but cannot sleepe,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Feare</hi> and <hi>Horrour</hi> do her eie-lids keepe.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <l>Murder sometime to slumber will betake her,</l>
                     <l>Till furie, wrath, and vengeance do awake her:</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon a Gentlewoman who died in Child-birth.</head>
                     <l>One, and my onely one lies buried heere,</l>
                     <l>Who in the Birth she bore, was borne on <hi>Beere;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To him askes more, this for excuse appeares,</l>
                     <l>"Ioy can find words, but words are drown'd in teares.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:63"/>
                     <head>Vpon an Infant (his fathers first borne) was this written:</head>
                     <l>By this auouch I may, right sure I am,</l>
                     <l>That meagre <hi>Death's</hi> an vniust <hi>Tithingman,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This was my First, not Tenth, and we do say,</l>
                     <l>"With <hi>Tenth,</hi> not <hi>First</hi> we vse our <hi>Tithe</hi> to pay.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Gray.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gray</hi> was my name, gray were my haires of hue,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Gray</hi> to graue return'd, payes Natures due.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Graue.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Graue</hi> I was, where now you see,</l>
                     <l>Graue is all is granted me:</l>
                     <l>Yet with me my name I haue,</l>
                     <l>Since in graue doth lodge a <hi>Graue.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <l>Iesu Christ my soule he saue,</l>
                     <l>Ere my Met-wand tuch my graue.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ Vpon one <hi>Winde</hi> towards the North-bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders is this written;</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Winde</hi> I'se can'd an new I find,</l>
                     <l>An mans life is but a wind;</l>
                     <l>Whilke an I had winde at will,</l>
                     <l>I had yet bene liuing still:</l>
                     <l>But I's, wele, though wind be gaue,</l>
                     <l>Siker I's wind feele I nane.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:64"/>
                     <head>¶ Another.</head>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="bottom">Hoc Epitaphtum are insculptum vidimus cathedrali templo Ebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racensi, pulcherrimo more (in aerea quadam lamina) consitum, sed baerbarie temporis magis excusanda, aut ineptia Autoris non satis miranda, parum condite dispositum in Orientali <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> prope me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam partem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> erigitur.</note>
                        <hi>Miseremini mei</hi> my Friends all,</l>
                     <l>For now the World hath enformed me to fall;</l>
                     <l>I must no longer endure, <hi>Pray for my Soule,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For the World is transitory and terrestriall.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>¶ Vpon old <hi>Mammon.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Here lies experienc'd Prouidence, whose care</l>
                     <l>Hath well enrich'd himself, made <hi>others</hi> bare;</l>
                     <l>And yet when Nature did denie <hi>Him</hi> breath,</l>
                     <l>Wormes had their <hi>Legacie</hi> by meanes of <hi>Death:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pray for his Soule,</hi> who prai'd on many a <hi>Soule,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>"And <hi>houle</hi> amaine when as the Bell doth toule:</l>
                     <l>The reason is, if you doe aske me why,</l>
                     <l>"<hi>Howling</hi> should supply mourning when <hi>Dogs</hi> die.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Animae meae propitietur Deus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ On a Cobler at <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Maruell not much though death in doubt did stand,</l>
                     <l>He found him alwayes on the <hi>mending</hi> hand;</l>
                     <l>Yet by misfortune and by change of weather,</l>
                     <l>Death ript his <hi>Soule</hi> quite from the vpper leather.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:64"/>
                     <head>¶ Vpon an Eminent STATESMAN in this Land, absolute for his generall suruey in all know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, his approued iudgement in all Learning.</head>
                     <l>Reade <hi>STATESMAN</hi> here thy owne mortalitie,</l>
                     <l>O meditate of <hi>Death</hi> before thy death;</l>
                     <l>Be not transport'd with <hi>Honour:</hi> for if we</l>
                     <l>Ere can shew <hi>vertue,</hi> it is while we breath,</l>
                     <l>Raising our hopes 'boue Earths felicity,</l>
                     <l>To crown our <hi>Temples</hi> with <hi>Fames</hi> glorious wreath:</l>
                     <l>Behold I <hi>was,</hi> and being was admir'd,</l>
                     <l>Elected <hi>STATESMAN,</hi> and esteemed fit</l>
                     <l>At all assaies of <hi>STATE,</hi> to manage it;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So</hi> all that <hi>Frame</hi> which <hi>was so</hi> much desir'd,</l>
                     <l>Ends in <hi>this Chest,</hi> where <hi>STATE</hi> retires expir'd.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ In the memory of that famous Professour of Physicke, M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
                        <hi>Butler,</hi> generally renowmed for his approued practice.</head>
                     <l>Death might dissolue thy forme, but not thy fame,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>shee</hi> hath reared on <hi>thee</hi> such a frame</l>
                     <l>As shall preserue thy mem'rie, sure I am,</l>
                     <l>So long as Age shall neede <hi>Physician;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cease Criticke then for to traduce his worth</l>
                     <l>Whose <hi>Oyle</hi> though it be spent, his <hi>Light's</hi> not forth.</l>
                     <l>"To sundry States our sundry Fates <hi>vs</hi> call,</l>
                     <l>Some for the <hi>Soule,</hi> some <hi>bodie</hi> few for all:</l>
                     <l>Yet we in way of Charity should know</l>
                     <l>"<hi>He</hi> had <hi>receits</hi> for Soule and Bodie too.<note n="*" place="margin">Sic Aesculapius exit, &amp; vrnam in quam omnes redeunt, repetit Supremam.</note>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <pb facs="tcp:178199:65"/>
                     <head>¶ On one <hi>More.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Here lies <hi>More,</hi> and no more but he,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>More,</hi> and no more, how can that be?</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ On one <hi>Pricke.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> they both their arrowes nicke,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> shot short, but <hi>Death</hi> he hit the <hi>Pricke.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon Sir Ignorance.</head>
                     <l>Here lies the body of <hi>Sir Ignorance,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who liued in a mist, died in a trance;</l>
                     <l>And may <hi>he</hi> so long sleepe where <hi>he</hi> is laine,</l>
                     <l>Till <hi>he</hi> forget to come to <hi>vs</hi> againe.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="epitaph">
                     <head>¶ Vpon Gregorie Cade.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sib my wife</hi> did promise me</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shee</hi> would die when I did die,</l>
                     <l>But no trust's in <hi>Her</hi> I see,</l>
                     <l>And you see't as well as I:</l>
                     <l>For my shrowde was scantly rotten,</l>
                     <l>Till my <hi>Sib</hi> had me forgotten.</l>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178199:65"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>